81ee
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Comedy &#8211; NotesOfLit</title>
	<atom:link href="https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/category/comedy/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit</link>
	<description>A Site FIlled With Literary Notes</description>
	<lastBuildDate>
	Tue, 16 Apr 2019 21:39:10 +0000	</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.1.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/cropped-cropped-Logo-32x32-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Comedy &#8211; NotesOfLit</title>
	<link>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Way of the World Written By William Congreve (1670-1729)</title>
		<link>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/2019/04/16/way-of-the-world-written-by-william-congreve-1670-1729/</link>
				<comments>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/2019/04/16/way-of-the-world-written-by-william-congreve-1670-1729/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2019 21:35:55 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ayan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Comedy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[1700]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Way of the World]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[William Congreve]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[World]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/?p=50</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[Restoration Comedy of Manners: “The Way of the World” which is written by William Congreve (1670-1729), remiered in 1700, is the most apposite example of comedy of manners with its witty dialogues between the characters, criticism of the upper class people’s manners and also satiric and effective scenes and proviso &#8230;]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h5>Restoration Comedy of Manners: “The Way of the World” which is written by William Congreve (1670-1729), remiered in 1700, is the most apposite example of comedy of manners with its witty dialogues between the characters, criticism of the upper class people’s manners and also satiric and effective scenes and proviso scene that ends in a lyrical celebration of unity. This comedy contains almost all the qualities which we find in a Restoration comedy and thus representing the peak and the perfection of this type of comedy. It presents a vast vista of contemporary social morality and principles and maintains a satirical tone from the beginning to the end. It gives us valuable information about the sophisticated class of society in England at that time.</h5>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<p>The Comedy of Manners also termed as a Restoration comedy is a witty and cerebral form of dramatic comedy that depicts and often satirizes the manners and affectations of a contemporary society. “The comedy of manners deals with the relations and intrigues of men and women living in a sophisticated upper-class society, and relies for comic effect in large part on the wit and sparkle of the dialogue—often in the form of repartee, a witty conversational give-and-take which constitutes a kind of verbal fencingmatch—as well as on the violations of social standards and decorum by would be wits, jealous husbands, conniving rivals, and foppish dandies”. The themes of the Restoration comedy of manners are love, marriage, adulterous relationships amours and legacy conflicts; and the characters generally include would be wits, jealous husbands, conniving rivals foppish dandies, fanatics, fools, imitators of French customs, conceited wits, and flirts. These plays are often centered around love and adultery and include gossip, eavesdropping, and scheming. Conversation is often witty and ironic. The Restoration period was an age of loose morals and, and was devoid of moral values. The Way of the World contains this current through the illicit love and adulterous relations – e.g. relation between Fainall and Mrs. Marwood, between Mirabell, the hero, and Mrs. Fainal. Mirabell married Mrs. Fainall off to Fainal, being afraid of her being pregnant. Fainall’s illicit relationship with Mrs. Marwood having been exposed, Fainall faces the situation fearlessly and shamelessly: “If it must all come out, why let ‘them know it; it’s but the way of the world.” Even Mrs. Marwood and Lady Wishfort secretly loved Mirabell. Unhappy conjugal life can be treated as another characteristic of the time which is expressed through the relation between Mr. and Mrs. Fainall. One of them feels uneasy in the presence of another. Mrs. Fainall expresses her uneasiness in St ames’s park in the presence of her husband- “He turned sort upon me unaware, and had almost overcome me.” The institution of marriage was always held to ridicule. Both husbands and wives openly expressed their dissatisfaction of their spouses. Mrs. wood says, “I have done hating &#8217;em, and am now come to despise &#8217;em;&nbsp;the next thing I have to do is eternally to forget em.” The Way of The World also exposes the worldliness and greed of the young men of the time. Mercenary motives led them to seek rich heiresses in marriage. Mr. Fainall marries Mrs. Fainall, a widow, for her property. Mirabell does not want to marry Millament without her property. This mercenary tendency led them to intrigue which was the order of the day in social and domestic life. Mirabell, in order to obtain Milament with her whole legacy, pretends to woo Lady Wishfort. He marries off his servant to Wishfort’s maid and sends his servant as Sir Roland to Lady Wishfort so that the servant can make a marriage contact with the lady. Even Sir Wilfull, an exception to other characters of the play, joins the web of intrigues in the play. Moreover, Fainall makes the legacy-conflict deeper through his cruel condition to Lady Wishfort. In The Way of The World, we are acquainted with the vanities, affectations and fashions of the time. Mirrabell satirically remarks in the proviso scene on women’s fondness of wearing masks, going to the theatre with or without their husbands’ knowledge, idle gossip, slandering the absent friends etc. In her contact with Mirabell, Millament proves her habit of late rising, contemplation in solitude general laziness etc. She says, “I’ll ye abed in a morning as long as I please.” Mirabell also ridicules pregnant women’s wearing tight dresses in order to maintain their figure. Moreover, intelligent women like Millament allowed a crowd of admirers to a school of fools to gather around them in order to show their demand and worth. Millament’s vanity is revealed in causing her lover pain to have a sense of power: “One’s cruelty is one’s power.” Above all, Lady Wishfort, a higher class fashionable lady, seeks a husband in her age of fifty five. Mirabell ridicules her saying, “The good lady would marry anything that resembled a men.” And the make up and dressing up of women of the society is expressed in the speech of the footman about Lady Wishfort of the house- “I cannot swear to her face in a morning, before she is dressed.” The upper class people could give up anything only to maintain/save the family name and fame. Lady Wishfort wants to conceal the scandal of her daughter by any means. She says, “I’ll compound, I’ll give up all, myself and my all, my niece and her all- anything, everything for composition.” The Way of The World brings before us witty Restoration ladies and gentlemen even their servants and fools are witty. As a result, the dialogue is throughout witty which is something unrealistic.. Therefore the play, like other plays of its kind, is called an ‘artificial’ comedy. From Footman’s speech we know about frequent changing of servantsin that society. Asked by Willfull about how long he is here, the Footman replies, “A week sir: longer than anybody in the house, except my lady’s woman.” Complicated plot construction is also regarded as a quality of comedy of manners. In this play, the five acts contain sixty five scenes in total, and there are very complicated relations among the characters. Such as, Mirabell, the hero is loved by Millament, Mrs. Fainall, Mrs. Marwood, and even Lady Wishfort secretly. He had a relation with Mrs. Fainall, onced tried to woo Lady wishfort and now trying to marry Millament. Witty dialogue and repartee are perhaps the most important features of the Comedy of Manners. The best example of a scene of witty dialogue is the &#8216;proviso&#8217; scene in which Millamant specifies her conditions before she agrees to accept Mirabell as her husband and he in turn also states his conditions. Millamant insists, “Let us be as strange as if we had been married a great while, and as well-bred as if we were not married at all.” To sum up, the whole plot of the play revolves around the issues of adultery, marriage and fortune hunting and mocks the society, or in other ways lift up society for scrutiny, which could cause negative or positive results. Congreve’s writing style shows both intelligence and sympathy with his creativity of the characters fixed with the aspects of the Restoration Comedy. The selfish, absurd and unbalanced manners of the characters are criticises clearly with the ironic and satiric usage of Congreve. Also, the importance of witty dialogues cannot be disregarded as the absolute proofs of the comedy of manners. The discussion above makes it very much clear that The Way of the World presents a faithful picture of the manners of the restoration period and the eighteenth century social picture. Though when the play was first performed in 1700 it was not a huge success, but later on it was realized that the play is a classic example of comedy of manners and Congreve’s “magnum opus” or master work. Major Themes: The themes of The way of the world: After Charles II revived theater in 1660, a new kind of comedy, the comedy of manners exploded onto the English drama scene and remained the preferred style of theater for the rest of the century. The aim of these plays was to mock society, or rather to hold it up for scrutiny by those very people whose social world was being characterized on stage. The Way of the World reflects Congreve&#8217;s personal view of Restoration society and city life, full of its artificiality, rigidity, and formality. As is typical of Restoration Theater, this play&#8217;s main themes are centered around that of marriage, money, love, social reputation, artificiality in manners, law, legacy conflicts, conspiracy, double status, adulterous relationships amours; and the characters generally include would be wits, jealous husbands, conniving rivals and foppish dandies. Love a la Mode: Certainly, the play can be seen as a dramatic presentation of varieties of love in the England of the year 1700. Central is the delicate handling of the love game as played by Mirabell and Millamant. They represent the ideal of the Restoration attitude, intense yet balanced, their love based on mutual esteem with no surrender of individuality. Contrasted with it are Mirabell&#8217;s earlier and quite ambiguous love affair with Mrs. Fainall; the illicit love of Fainall and Mrs. Marwood, presumably passionate, but wholly without mutual trust; the spurious court young Witwoud pays to Millamant; the direct and somewhat coarse approach of Sir Wilfull; and, at the opposite extreme completely, the aging and undignified longings of Lady Wishfort, vain, unrealistic, over-eager, desperate, and a little pathetic. Love and Money: Money is a distinct concern for several of the characters in Congreve’s play. In the world whose way is presented here, love and money are values to be taken into account at all times. The sentiment of love itself is not enough to build a romantic relationship on or to protect family bonds. Money is actually an indispensible ingredient of love as money provides for a comfortable life, which then allows one to enjoy one’s love. The dominant Restoration attitude was that while love is important, but it must not obscure the importance of money. Mirabell’s love for Millament is genuine, but he will not let the ‘moiety’ of her fortune go. The sincerity of Mirabell&#8217;s love does not make him lose sight of the importance of Millamant&#8217;s fortune. Fainall marries for money to support an illicit love; apparently the thought of marrying Mrs. Marwood without adequate money is unthinkable. Money is Lady Wishfort&#8217;s sole hold over her child and her ward. Even the marriage of the servants itself is also a testament to this theme. It is built on a promise of a handsome sum of money. This is the world&#8217;s way. Love without money is an impossible sentimental dream, although money often corrupts what love there is. Marriage: Marriages are central thematic concerns as Mirabell’s machinations are fuelled by his desire to marry Millamant, and Fainall uses his marriage to try to extract money from his mother-in-law, Lady Wishfort. The state of marriage is depicted as simultaneously desirable, and yet to be avoided as a trap should be. These aspects of marriage are used to comic effect, but the play ends finally with a warning against falsehood in the marriage bed and so reminds the readers and the audience that it is dishonesty in marriage rather than marriage that has been questioned here. Dishonesty and disloyalty is depicted as a core feature of marriage in Way of the world. Mrs. Fainall had a relationship with Mirabel but married Fainall to avoid rumours or unwanted pregnancy… Mr. Fiannal and Mrs. Marwood has an adulterous relationship though Mr. Fainall is married to … Marriage was dependent on the social status, money and power that the individuals possessed. It was unheard of, at that time, to marry solely for love. The highly contrived plot of&nbsp;The Way of the World&nbsp;reflects these preoccupations with money and status. Even though Mirabell loves Millament, he is unwilling to let go of her inheritance. The entire plot is designed to allow the two to marry with Lady Wishfort’s permission. While marriages are important economic contracts, they are also convenient vehicles for protecting social reputations. Mrs. Fainall has made such a marriage, which is socially acceptable and even expected, as long as the pretense of civility is maintained. Jungle of High Intrigue: In this play everyone is engaged in intrigue: Mirabell intrigues to gain consent to his marriage from Lady Wishfort, and this involves intrigue within intrigue, for he does not trust Waitwell. Fainall intrigues in turn. Everyone is involved in one or the other of these schemes&#8211;Mrs. Fainall, Mrs. Marwood, and the servants. Even Lady Wishfort in her willingness to marry Sir Rowland has a devious purpose&#8211;revenge on Mirabell. When Mrs. Fainall married her husband, that was part of an intrigue, as was his marriage to her. And as we see in the play, victory goes to Mirabell, not because of his virtue, but simply because he is the most successful intriguer. Social Etiquette and Reputation: &#8220;Why do we daily commit disagreeable and dangerous actions? To save that idol, reputation.&#8221; (Act II, Scene II) A Comedy of Manners is named as such to call attention to one of its most central themes &#8211; manners, or social etiquette, and the comedy that can ensue because of the importance, especially to the upper class during the Restoration, of preserving one&#8217;s position in society. In the climax of the play, the actions and reactions largely stop being concerned with love or even money, and what Lady Wishfort seems to fear most is a loss of good reputation for herself and her daughter. Much of the demonstrated love seen in the show &#8211; for example, Witwoud and Petulant&#8217;s love for Ms. Millamant &#8211; is done purely in hopes of raising one&#8217;s reputation. Fun is made of social etiquette especially in the acting of Petulant, Sir Wilfull, and Sir Rowland, three characters that to varying degrees are unable to live up to upper class standards, but must try to put on a show for others. Friendship: Same-gender and opposite gender friendships are called into question in this play, as it is said and demonstrated that none of these relationships is particularly strong or trusting. The women-women and men-men pairings, though originally posing as friends, join schemes against one another based mostly on money and reputation. As for women-men pairings, we do not see many in the play that are not based on either mutual love or the love of one and disdain of the other. Certainly, friendship is as falsely fashionable and tactical as anything else in the play. Social Convention: Congreve&#8217;s ‘‘comedy of manners’’ takes the fashionable or conventional social behavior of the time as the principle subject of satire. Conflicts that arise between and among characters are prompted by affected and artificial social mores, especially with respect to relationships between the sexes. Social pretenses and plot complications abound in&nbsp;The Way of the World. Women are compelled to act coyly and to dissemble in courtship; couples deceive one another in marriage; friends are double-dealing, and conquests have more to do with dowries and convenience than love. All moral principle is risked for the sake of reputation and money. However, what makes the action comic is the subterfuge. What one says is hardly ever what one really thinks or means. To judge by appearances, for example, no one could be happier in his marriage than Fainall, who in reality disdains his wife and is carrying on an adulterous affair with his wife&#8217;s close friend. Congreve intimates that, in fashionable society at the turn of the eighteenth century, it is crucial to preserve the outer trappings of beauty, wit, and sophistication no matter how egregious one&#8217;s actions and words might prove. Significance of the title: “The Way of the World” which is written by William Congreve (1670-1729), premiered in 1700, is the most apposite example of comedy of manners with its witty dialogues between the characters, criticism of the upper class people’s manners and also satiric and effective scenes that ends in a lyrical celebration of unity. The title of this play is significant because it points to one of the major themes of the play &#8212; it sort of signals to us what the play is about. The way of the word generally means, the manner in which people typically behave or things typically happen. The play is a &#8220;comedy of manners&#8221; in which the playwright pokes fun at the social customs and values of his time.&nbsp; He makes fun of marriages and dowries and he makes fun of the way men and women behave towards each other. The title of the play is rightly suitable, first, it is inspired by the then social period during which the play was originally performed. Secondly, as a comedy of manners, it makes fun of human follies and silly social behaviors. But some critics also suggest that The Way of the World&nbsp;points to the ‘way’ the hero and heroine should adopt in order to come out of the grip of the fashionable society. The entire play is set in London and this urban setting keeps especial importance. It basically represents metropolitan aristocratic society and ridiculed people for their lack of sophistication.&nbsp; The Act 1 begins in the chocolate house where many people come to enjoy. Similarly, Act II begins in St. James Park. The park suggests something as freedom. This is a public place where basically fashionable people use to go to exchange their heart and to be free. Act III, too, begins in Lady Wishforts’ house, but the very scene is in the toilet. Remaining inside the toilet, Lady Wishfort is talking to Peg in serious matters. It clearly shows that how restoration people take the serious things lightly. In Act IV, lady Wishfort and Foible are talking the arrival of Sir Roland. Lady Wishfort orders to Foible to arrange the things in order and she also asks for dancer and musician if he (Sir Roland) wants to entertain. It is the showy nature of the Restoration period (people). Because people like Lady Wishfort is very much concerned on how to perceive and impress man in his first visit. As a result, she talks how to sit, how to walk, how to talk in front of him. She says, ‘I will walk from the door upon his entrance and how do I look?’ These some events clearly show that how the restoration people are very pedantic in their fashion and outer appearance. In the same way, in another scene, Millamant talks with her lover Mirabell that she does not like to be familiar or found, she rejects to go any park not she plays together, even after the marriage, and she wants to be like unmarried one. Likewise, she wants liberty to write letters, to receive letters, to talk with a lover, to have dinner with him and to bring him in her dressing room. Even her husband must knock the door, before entering the room if her lover is inside the room. These are the general condition she talks with Mirabell before getting married. This is what actually the Restoration period was. In the play male characters are pursuing women. We can take the instance of Mirabell, Witwood, Petuland and Fainall who seem adulterous and deceptive. It was because fashionable to court a young and beautiful woman in the contemporary society. In the play, everyone plots against everyone and deceives everyone. And the play begins, we know that Mirabell pretends to love Lady Wishfort in order to be touched with Millamant, the single heir of the property. Mr. Finall, the fortune hunter is also committed to get Millament’s fortune at hand. We find the characters in disguise and they do their best to be what they are not. To pretend to be what one is not is the way of the world. So, the title itself suggests the manner of Restoration urban aristocrats. The very title of the play,&nbsp;The Way of the World&nbsp;points to the ‘way’ the hero and heroine should adopt in order to come out of the grip of the fashionable society. The whole story is an illustration of the process, by following which Mirabell and Millament seek a resolution, that is, to gain their own world by using and manipulating the existing social norms, through the winding lanes of that society. Congreve constructed the plot of the play accordingly with this aim in mind. One can discern a definite pattern in the movement of the play. At the beginning of the play, Mirabell is trying to shape up a situation so that he can win both hands of Millament and her estate from Lady Wishfort. He has married his servant, Waitwell off to Lady Wishfort’s maid, Foible and plans to have Waitwell disguise himself as a noble man, court, and marry Lady Wishfort. Then Mirabell would blackmail her by threatening to disclose that she has married a servant and would offer her to release her if she will let him marry Millament plus the estate. But Mrs. Marwood discovers the plan and tells Lady Wishfort. Mrs. Marwood also tells Fainwall of his wife, Mrs. Fainwall’s former relationship with Mirabell. From all these Fainwall plans to blackmail Lady Wishfort by threatening to reveal all unless she signs over to him not only his wife’s but also Millament’s estate and even the conversation of Lady Wishfort’s own estate after her death. As the action of the play gets momentum and the plot becomes more and more complicated, Congreve loads the stage by introducing confusing figures like Mr. Wilful Witwood. While it adds to the comedy of the play, it complicates the plot further. However, certain hidden facts of the past are revealed through the conversations of the characters: for instance, Mrs. Marwood’s desire for Mirabell, Mrs. Marwood’s relationship with Fainall, Mirabell’s past affair with Mrs. Fainall etc. Congreve measures these secrets slowly person by person, until the final revelation in Act V, where all pretences are destroyed Mr. Fainall’s and Mirabell’s revelations, and the bringing out from a black box of the deed renders Mr. Fainall powerless. The complexities and complications are, however, deliberate on Congreve’s part; for he wanted to present his Restoration audience a play that can coincide artistically with the artificialities and complexities in the human affairs of the period. The chief aim of the dramatist is to demonstrate “the way of the world”. Following this way Mirabell and Millament, through their own peculiar balance of wit and generosity of spirit, reduce the bumbling Witwood and Mr. Fainall to the same level of false wit. Thus the pair dramatise the true wit that is carefully and symmetrically defined through their opposition. They are aware of the fact that they are making compromises in their marriage. Mirabell says, “…I like her with all her faults: nay, I like her for her faults…They are now grown familiar to me as my own frailties…” And Millament charmingly declares, “Well, if Mirabell should not make a good husband, I am lost thing—find I love him violently.” These confidences do not prevent their own chances for honesty in marriage. In the Proviso Scene they arrange an agreement for their marriage. The reason is obvious: that is, marriage is a social contract that would enable them to rise above the cant and hypocrisy that surround them. The triumph of the play is in the emergence of lovers who through a balance of intense affection and cool self-knowledge achieve an equilibrium that frees them from the world’s power. As the title of the play&nbsp;The Way of the World&nbsp;suggests, they have assimilated the rational lucidity of skeptical rake so that they can use the world and reject its demands. Beneath the surface of proper English society are layers of deceit, greed, vanity, pretension, silliness, desire for revenge, and indecorous romance. Congreve&#8217;s sharp wit pierces this surface to reveal society as it is, with all its faults, foibles, follies, and bitter rivalries. He shows the reader “the way of the world.&#8221; Proviso Scene: It was quite common for Restoration comedies to have Proviso scenes, that is, scenes where the hero and heroine define a set of rules which they would like the other to follow in order to facilitate a balanced relationship. In a way they are setting the parameters of an equal marriage. the Proviso Scene is one of the most remarkable aspects of William Congreve&#8217;s(1670-1729) &#8220;The Way of the World&#8221;(1700). In Act 4 of The Way of the World, couple Mirabell and Millamont find themselves in a battle of wit as they discuss the terms of their marriage. This scene, called the proviso scene, gives important insight into Mirabell and Millamont&#8217;s relationship. The terms of both characters illustrate their concerns and fears for their future marriage. The scene is a pure comedy with brilliant display of wit by both of them, but, above all, provides instructions which have serious dimensions in the context of the society. Mirabell and Millament both are well-acquainted with the ‘Way of the World’, and see the Provisos as a way to a stable future, where both can have their freedom. They lay down a set of rules which they would like the other to comply to. Mirabell sounds patronising and sententious, yet his provisos reveal that he is not altogether insensitive. He reveals his thoughtfulness and his foresight when he declares that he wants no intrigue in his house, and if that condition is fulfilled, he would agree to be a “tractable and complying husband”. Mirabell and Millamant’s marriage will be different from the other relationships in the play because it would be based on mutual respect and love. The nature of their provisos shows their genuine love for each other.&nbsp;They will forge a new Way of the World with their marriage and the Provisos each sets for the other shows that they genuinely care for each other and are keen to be faithful in their marriage. Through this scene appears very funny but it is a serious comment on the degradation of conjugal relations. The conditions as set down by the two lovers, confirm the sincerity of their motives and their wish to live a married life which was different from others. Both of them accept each other&#8217;s conditions. It is a guideline or memorandum of understanding between a husband and a wife, which would enable them to spend a happy married life. According to Millamant’s first condition, she wants equal amount of love and affection on the part of her would husband throughout her life. Behind her conditions one can notice the pitiable condition of a wife after marriage. Just before marriage when men and women are lovers they declare full support and love for each other but things take a turn when they marry each other. So Millamant appears anxious because of this reason and that is why she puts this condition. Again, Millamant says that she hates those lovers who do not take proper care of their beloveds. She further wants that her husband must be a loyal and good natured man.&nbsp; Millamants conditions shows that they will compromise but won’t bid adieu to their individuality and freedom. Millamant says to Mirabell that she wants her liberty after her marriage; she informs Mirabell that she can&#8217;t forgo her independence, she says, &#8220;My dear liberty, shall I leave thee? My faithful solitude, my darling contemplation, must I bid you adiue?&#8230; My morning, thoughts, agreeable wakings, indolent slumbers, all ye douceurs, &#8230; Adieu &#8212; I can&#8217;t do it, &#8217;tis more than impossible.&#8221; She also adds that &#8220;I will lie a bed in a morning as long as I please&#8221;. Even she demands that she can receive and pay visits and letters to anyone she pleases. In the former scene one can see that Mr. and Mrs. Fainal, though don’t have any love or care for each other, addresses each other as “my dear”, “my soul” in public just to go with the flow of social decorum. But Millament criticizes this public “show off” and informs that she would not like to be addressed by such names as “wife, spouse, my dear, joy, jewel, love, sweet-heart; and the rest of that nauseous can, in which men and their wives are so fulsomely familiar.” Moreover, they will continue to present a decorous appearance in public. In other words, after marriage they maintain certain distance and reserve between them. She says, “Let us be as strange as if we had been marry’d a great while; and as well bred as if we are not marry’d at all.” Each of Mirabell’s provisos begin with its item: first, the general principle, “that your Acquaintance be general”, then specific instructions, “no she-friend to screen her affairs”, no fop to take her to the theatre secretly, and an illustration of the forbidden behaviour, “to wheedle you a fop-scrambling to the play in a mask”. Nevertheless, Mirabell denounces the use of tight dresses during pregnancy by women, and he forbids the use of alcoholic drinks. Though at first his conditions seems patronizing gradually they proved his genuine love and concern for her. The conditions are stated by both parties in a spirit of fun and gaiety, but the fact remained that both are striving to arrive at some kind of mutual understanding. Mirabells conditions also mocked some flaws in social practices. In that century women used to put a heavy makeup to hide their flaws which consume a lot of time and energy. Act III scene I is a nice example of this practice. But Mirabell criticizes this practice by one of his conditions. He says Millamant should not use the artificial things to cover her real appearance. On that time people used to pay visits to one another and specially women used to criticize one another behind one’s back. One of Mirabell’s “article”s was, Millamant should not be in company of any woman who has a notorious background or who indulges in scandalous activities. This condition revels the practice of backbiting of the people of that time. In Congreve’s “The Way of the World” Congreve seems to come to realise the importance for providing an ideal pair of man and woman, ideal in the sense that the pair could be taken for models in the life-style of the period. In fact, it serves as an excellent medium through which Congreve conveys his message to his readers. The lovers negotiate in this scene for a mutual private happiness within the confines of a rigid and demanding social context and they establish their relationship upon the possibility of such reconciliation. They manage to be sincere in a world full of pretence and their love is in any case true love.<br></p>

e9
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/2019/04/16/way-of-the-world-written-by-william-congreve-1670-1729/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
	</channel>
</rss>

0

