<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Uncategorized &#8211; NotesOfLit</title>
	<atom:link href="https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/category/uncategorized/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit</link>
	<description>A Site FIlled With Literary Notes</description>
	<lastBuildDate>
	Wed, 17 Apr 2019 10:34:38 +0000	</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.1.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/cropped-cropped-Logo-32x32-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Uncategorized &#8211; NotesOfLit</title>
	<link>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Farie Queene Written By Edmund Spenser</title>
		<link>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/2019/04/17/farie-queene-written-by-edmund-spenser/</link>
				<comments>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/2019/04/17/farie-queene-written-by-edmund-spenser/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2019 10:34:38 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ayan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/?p=119</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[ALLEGORY: The Faerie Queene, written by Edmund Spenser in the late 1500s, is an allegorical tale created to teach its readers how to live up to the six virtues Spenser explores in each book. The first half was published in 1590 and a second installment in 1596. On a literal &#8230;]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h3>ALLEGORY:</h3>



<p class="has-drop-cap">The Faerie Queene, written by Edmund Spenser in the late 1500s, is an allegorical tale created to teach its readers how to live up to the six virtues Spenser explores in each book. The first half was published in 1590 and a second installment in 1596. On a literal level, the poem follows several&nbsp;knights&nbsp;in an examination of several virtues, though it is primarily an&nbsp;allegorical&nbsp;work, and can be read on several levels of allegory, including as praise of Queen&nbsp;Elizabeth I. Critics have long recognized&nbsp;The Faerie Queene&nbsp;as an allegorical tale, including within its many subplots a variety of political, social, psychological, and religious allegories. Allegory&nbsp;is a form of extended metaphor in which objects and persons&nbsp;within&nbsp;a narrative are equated with meanings that lie&nbsp;outside&nbsp;the narrative. According to J.D. Cuddon the term allegory is “any writing in verse or prose that has a double meaning”. In true Spenserian style, with everything having double meanings, both uses of the term allegory are applicable to his writing.&nbsp;Allegory implies&nbsp;two levels of meaning&nbsp;&#8211; the&nbsp;literal and the&nbsp;symbolic. It evokes a dual interest: in the events, characters and setting presented; and in the ideas they represent or the significance they bear. Allegory may involve the personification of abstract qualities (e.g. Pride, Beauty, Death); it can also represent a historical personage (e.g. Gloriana = Queen Elizabeth), a category of individual (e.g. Everyman = all mankind), or another sort of abstraction (Una = the True Church). In a letter to Sir Walter Ralegh, appended to the first, 1590, edition of The Faerie Queene, Spenser describes his exuberant, multifaceted poem as an allegory—an extended metaphor or &#8220;dark conceit&#8221;—and invites us to interpret the characters and adventures in the several books in terms of the particular virtues and vices they enact or come to embody. In the letter he states that the entire epic poem is &#8220;cloudily enwrapped in Allegorical devises,&#8221; and that the aim of publishing&nbsp;The Faerie Queene&nbsp;was to &#8220;fashion a gentleman or noble person in vertuous and gentle discipline&#8221;. However, Spenser&#8217;s allegory is not as simple as the letter to Ralegh might suggest. It has several levels of allegory: religious, historical, political, mythological. The more important purpose of the&nbsp;Faerie Queene&nbsp;is its allegory, the meaning behind its characters and events. The story&#8217;s setting, a fanciful &#8220;faerie land,&#8221; only emphasizes how its allegory is meant for a land very close to home: Spenser&#8217;s England. The title character, the Faerie Queene herself, is meant to represent Queen Elizabeth. She is introduced in Canto I and Red Cross Knight is introduced as the recipient of a mission from Gloriana that would end with him slaying a &#8220;dragon horrible and stearne&#8221;. The Dedication of&nbsp;The Faerie Queene&nbsp;establishes the connection between Elizabeth I and Gloriana. THE MOST HIGH, MIGHTIE, AND MAGNIFICENT EMPERESSE &#8230; ELIZABETH BY THE GRACE OF GOD &#8230; Defender of the Faith etc. HER MOST HUMBLE SERVAUNT EDMVND SPENSER DOTH IN ALL HUMILITIE DEDICATE, PRESENT, AND CONSECRATE THESE HIS LABOVRS TO LIVE WITH THE ETERNITIE OF HER FAME. (Dedication,&nbsp;The Faerie Queene) And if the Faerie Queene herself is consigned to the margins of the poem that bears her name, she nonetheless is the symbolic embodiment of a shared national destiny, a destiny that reaches beyond mere political success to participate in the ultimate, millennial triumph of good over evil. As a political allegory, Redcrosse represents the individual Christian, on the search for Holiness, who is armed with faith in Christ, the shield with the bloody cross. Red Cross, as an individual, is the Protestant Everyman, but as Saint George, historically England’s patron saint, he also represents the collective people of England. Prince Arthur is a character that also gives courtesy and respect to Lord Leicester. In Una we see a person of a fair lady of the court. In Archimago symbolizes the odious King Philip II of Spain, and Duessa represents Mary Queen of Scots. The dragon represents sin, the Spanish Armada, and the Beast of the Apocalypse, and when Red Cross defeats the dragon he is in effect restoring his beloved England. &#8220;Una&#8221; is also a name applied in this period to Queen Elizabeth, the one supreme governor of the Church of England. Elizabeth lived under constant threat of military attack or assassination by the great Catholic princes on the Continent, who wanted to reverse the Protestant Reformation in England and to return the nation to the Catholic fold. In the political allegory of the poem Duessa represents Mary, Queen of Scots, who had legal claims to the English crown and who vied with Elizabeth for the allegiance of the English people. The different characters stand for various religious events and dignitaries of age. The reformation was the most important religious movement of the time and in this epic Spenser has represented it allegorically. Book I is generally interpreted as a religious allegory concerning the split between the Catholic Church and the Church of England during the era of the English Reformation. The adventures of the Red Cross Knight are an allegory for the struggle of the individual between the forces of sin and holiness, as well as the struggles of England to assert itself as a Protestant nation against the threat of Catholic countries. In the course of Book I, The Red Cross Knight moves from the House of Pride, a den of sin, to the House of Holiness, where his Christian virtues are revitalized. The religious allegory of Book I may additionally be seen in the designation of Una&#8217;s parents as the King and Queen of Eden (Adam and Eve), whose home is under the thrall of a dragon, representing Satan. Critics have further interpreted Una as representative of the Church of England and the Red Cross Knight as the nation of England. Thus, their union at the end of Book I is an allegory for the union of the Anglican Church with the English monarchy and citizenry. The plot of&nbsp;Book I&nbsp;mostly concerns the attempts of evildoers to separate Red Cross from Una to decrease his strength. Most of these villains are meant by Spenser to represent one thing in common:&nbsp;the&nbsp;Roman Catholic Church. The poet felt that, in the&nbsp;English Reformation, the people had defeated “false religion” (Catholicism) and embraced “true religion” (Protestantism/Anglicanism).So Red Cross must defeat villains who mimic the falsehood of the Roman Church. In the course of his mission he and Una come upon various manifestations of evil. The first encounter is with monster&nbsp;Error. The monster Error allegorically stands for all sorts of mistakes which every individual makes in the course of his life. The fight of the Red Cross Knight with the monster Error symbolises the conflict between Protestantism and Catholicism. When Redcrosse chokes the beast, Spenser writes, &#8220;Her vomit full of bookes and papers was (I.i.20).&#8221; These papers represent Roman Catholic propaganda that was put out in Spenser&#8217;s time, against Queen Elizabeth and Anglicanism. The Red Cross Knight may able to defeat these obvious and disgusting errors, but until he is united to the truth he is totally lost and can be easily deceived. This deceit is arranged by Archimago, whose name means &#8220;arch-image&#8221;&#8211;the Protestants accused the Catholics of idolatry because of their extensive use of images. Archimago represents the cunningness and hypocrisy craftiness and lip service of Papacy. The sorcerer is able, through deception and lust, to separate Redcrosse from Una&#8211;that is, to separate Holiness from Truth. When Truth and Holiness are separated, Hypocrisy gets the chance to mislead Holiness. The separation of Truth from Holiness symbolises the danger of the English Church against the hypocrisy and plots of the Roman Catholicism. Once separated, Holiness is susceptible to the opposite of truth or falsehood. Red Cross, separated from Una, falls prey to the tricks of Falsehood herself –Duessa. Duessa also represents the Roman Church, both because she is “false faith”, and of her rich, purple and gold clothing, which, for Spenser, displays the greedy wealth and arrogant pomp of Rome. Historically Duessa stands for&nbsp;Queen Mary&nbsp;who was a Roman Catholic by faith. Red Cross becomes a veritable puppet in the hands of Duessa. In the similar manner Truth also becomes weak and in order to protect her virtue she gets aid and succor from&nbsp;Lion&nbsp;which stands for Courage. Thus at the end Spenser represents the triumph of Holiness and Truth. They may be separated by various evildoers but ultimately they are united again to bring about the redemption and moral salvation of human race. There is no matter of doubt that Spencer’s poem,&nbsp;The Faerie Queene, is replete with allegorical significance. Edmund Spenser stands among the greatest writers of the Elizabethan period whose valuable contributions fashioned a new tradition in English literature. Nowadays he is hailed to be one of the chief initiators of the Renaissance movement in English literature. Spenser’s rich and vigorous imagery and careful treatment of metrical structure left a profound influence on the succeeding poets and ensured his place as one of the seminal literary artists in the flamboyant field of English literature. A number of objections have been raised against Spenser&#8217;s use of allegory. The device is essentially a technique of vision, but Spenser&#8217;s use of it, instead of imparting clarity, confuses the story and perplexes the readers. All is confused and obscure, nothing is clear and comprehensible. Too many digressions, add further to the confusion of the readers. They may impart variety to the epic but they make the action loose rambling and discursive, and the story incoherent and meaningless. So the didactic purpose of the book is not achieved. According to Albert Charles Hamilton, “These episodes dramatize Spener’s bitter critique of the Roman Catholic church and his hope that in England at least it has been defeated”. Roberts is right in saying “Spenser’s allegorical poem demands the active engagement of its reader to produce allegory”. Each close reading provides the reader with a different allegory, and it is through these multiple interpretations that Spenser manages to reveal part of his overall political, religious, and moral messages.&nbsp;</p>



<h3>ALLUTION:</h3>



<p>Edmund Spenser&nbsp;(1552/1553 &#8211; 1599) was an English poet best known for&nbsp;The Faerie Queene, an epic poem and fantastical&nbsp;allegory&nbsp;celebrating the&nbsp;Tudor dynasty&nbsp;and&nbsp;Elizabeth I. The first three books of&nbsp;The Faerie Queene&nbsp;were published in 1590, and a second set of three books were published in 1596.&nbsp;DURING the sixteenth century the study of classical literature, which opened a new field to imagination, and gave it a new impulse, was eagerly and vigorously pursued. A classic ardour was widely and extensively diffused. The compositions of that age incessantly imitate and allude to the beauties and incidents of the writings of ancient Greece and Rome. In a letter addressed to Sir Walter Ralegh, Spenser sets out to explain the &#8220;general intention and meaning&#8221; of his richly elaborated epic. It is &#8220;an historicall fiction,&#8221; written to glorify Queen Elizabeth and &#8220;to fashion a gentleman or noble person in vertuous and gentle discipline.&#8221; Elsewhere in his letter, he alludes to this point directly, “I have followed the all the antique poets historical: first Homer … then Virgil … after him Ariosto … and lately Tasso … By ensample of which excellent poets, I labour to portrait in Arthur … the image of a brave knight … the which is the purpose of these first twelve books.” Spenser explicitly cites two classical and two vernacular models for his work:&nbsp; the Greek&nbsp;epic&nbsp;poet&nbsp;Homer, author of the&nbsp;The Odyssey; the Roman epic poet&nbsp;Virgil, author of the&nbsp;Aeneid; and the Italian poets&nbsp;Ariosto and Tasso, authors of the &#8220;romantic epic&#8221; works&nbsp;Orlando Furioso&nbsp;and&nbsp;Gerusalemme liberata, respectively.&nbsp; Like the Italian &#8220;romantic epics,&#8221; Spenser&#8217;s&nbsp;Faerie Queene&nbsp;contains both&nbsp;epic&nbsp;and&nbsp;romance&nbsp;elements. But it is clear that he is primarily interested in establishing himself not as the English Ariosto but as the &#8220;new Virgil&#8221;. Spenser’s idea that each protagonist of The Faerie Queene should represent and idealize a different private, Christian virtue, has its genesis within the work of Virgil. Aeneas, the hero displaced from Troy and predestined ancestor of the Roman people, was deliberately portrayed to represent the Stoic ideal, as admired by Virgil and any Romans as the Protestant ideal was dear to Spenser and his fellow Englishmen. Part of Virgil’s purpose was to inspire men to follow Aeneas’ example of a man who perseveres and endures despite insurmountable obstacles. Virgil accomplishes this by telling a focused tale of heroic actions, while Spenser give a fragmented narrative full of breaks in the action and digressions. For Spenser, it is not the narrative that inspires men to emulate great deeds, but extensive allegory, relying heavily on subtext to power his meaning. A first example of how Spenser achieves these ambitious poetic goals is found in the&nbsp;four opening stanzas&nbsp;of the poem. Spenser&#8217;s reworking of the classical&nbsp;epic element&nbsp;of the&nbsp;Invocation of the Muse&nbsp;in stanzas 1 and 2, in which he explicitly compares himself to&nbsp;Virgil: both turned from youthful works in the&nbsp;pastoral mode&nbsp;to the higher form of the&nbsp;epic. Spenser thus likens his poetic enterprise in writing the FQ to that of Virgil in writing the greatest of all Latin epics, the&nbsp;Aeneid. Note also the&nbsp;twelve-part structure&nbsp;of the FQ (cf. 623, 625): there were to have been twelve books, each containing twelve cantos; Spenser&#8217;s model is again&nbsp;Virgil&#8217;s&nbsp;Aeneid, which is also made up of twelve books.&nbsp; The same desire to associate his poetic enterprise with that of&nbsp;Virgil&nbsp;is found in the implicit reference to Virgil in line 9, &#8220;Fierce&nbsp;warres and faithfull&nbsp;loves&nbsp;shall&nbsp;moralize&nbsp;my&nbsp;song.&#8221; This line is an adaptation of Virgil&#8217;s famous statement of his own epic subject matter in the&nbsp;opening line&nbsp;of the&nbsp;Aeneid: &#8220;I&nbsp;sing&nbsp;of&nbsp;warfare&nbsp;and a&nbsp;man at war&#8230;&#8221; (trans. Robert Fitzgerald). On the literal level, FQ is obviously the tale of RCK&#8217;s heroic completion of a dangerous quest: he must defeat an evil dragon, thereby liberating both Una&#8217;s parents and their kingdom. This quest is reminiscent of the exploits of epic figures such as&nbsp;Beowulf, Odysseus/Ulysses&nbsp;or&nbsp;Aeneas. A&nbsp;Romance&nbsp;element is however introduced into the epic formula by the fact that RCK has undertaken the quest at the request of a lady, Una, who is also his love interest. There are numerous other&nbsp;epic elements&nbsp;in the FQ: one of the most notable is the&nbsp;descent into Hell&nbsp;described in&nbsp;C.&nbsp;5, st. 31-44. Since&nbsp;Virgil&#8217;s&nbsp;Aeneid, a trip to the underworld has been considered an obligatory episode in an epic work; any epic poet worth his salt has to include one, because it is expected, and because it lets him claim his work is as good as Virgil&#8217;s. Again, Spenser may have been inspired by the great 14th-century Italian poet&nbsp;Dante, who devoted an entire book of his Christian epic poem, the&nbsp;Divine Comedy, to a first-person account of his journey through Hell. In the&nbsp;Inferno, Dante the poet must travel through Hell on his way to Christian truth because he has gotten lost in a wilderness reminiscent of the &#8220;wandring woods&#8221; where RCK goes astray in FQ c.&nbsp;1. There is also a shorter visit to the underworld in c.&nbsp;1, where Archimago sends messengers to Morpheus to obtain the false dreams he will use to deceive RCK (1.36-47). Spenser may have borrowed his terminology from Dante as well: &#8220;canto&#8221; is the Italian word for song, and is used to describe the divisions of Dante&#8217;s poem. Spenser includes a&nbsp;LOVE ELEMENT&nbsp;not present in classical epic; instead, it is borrowed from one of Spenser&#8217;s other literary models, medieval&nbsp;Arthurian romance&nbsp;(cf. the reference to &#8220;Knights and Ladies gentle deeds&#8221; in line 5), and from the Italian &#8220;romantic epics&#8221; of&nbsp;Tasso and Ariosto; these romantic epics similarly grafted &#8220;love stuff&#8221; onto the classical, war- and male-oriented epic model found in&nbsp;Virgil, the Greek epic poet Homer, or&nbsp;Beowulf. This new influx of the &#8220;love&#8221; element into a previously male- and war-oriented form is also suggested by Spenser&#8217;s reference to&nbsp;Cupid&nbsp;in stanza 3, as well as by the invocation of both&nbsp;Venus, the classical Goddess of Love, and&nbsp;Mars, the classical God of War, in the same stanza: they will assist the nine&nbsp;Muses&nbsp;in helping Spenser present the&nbsp;&#8220;warres&#8221; and &#8220;faithfull loves&#8221;&nbsp;alluded to in line 9. The poem celebrates, memorializes, and critiques the&nbsp;Tudor dynasty, much as&nbsp;Virgil&#8217;s Aeneid&nbsp;celebrates Augustus Caesar&#8217;s Rome. The&nbsp;Aeneid&nbsp;states that Augustus descended from the noble sons of&nbsp;Troy; similarly,&nbsp;The Faerie Queene&nbsp;suggests that the Tudor lineage can be connected to King Arthur. The poem is deeply allegorical&nbsp;and&nbsp;allusive; many prominent Elizabethans could have found themselves partially represented by one or more of Spenser&#8217;s figures. Elizabeth herself is the most prominent example. She appears in the guise of Gloriana, the Faerie Queen. THe circumstance of the Red-cross knight and Una meeting with Archimago disguised like a hermit, who tells them a feign&#8217;d tale, and after that raises two spirits with an intent to deceive the Red∣cross Knight, seems to be copied from Ariosto, who introduces Angelica meeting with an hypocritical hermit who raises a false spirit with a design to deceive Sacrapant and Renaldo, and to exasperate them against Orlando, &amp;c. But Spenser has greatly improv&#8217;d the hint. Many characters of Spenser’s Feire queene is based on classical stories. An aged Sire,&nbsp;the false enchanter, Archimago, or Hypocrisy, who is supposed to represent Pope Sixtus V or King Philip II of Spain generally stands for false religion or the Church of Rome. The character and adventure are taken from&nbsp;Orlando Furioso, ii, 12, in which there is a hypocritical hermit. The description of the monster Error, or Falsehood, is based on Hesiod&#8217;s Echidna,&nbsp;Theog. 301, and the locusts in&nbsp;Revelation, ix, 7-10. She is half human, half serpent, because error is partly true and partly false. Dante&#8217;s Fraud and Milton&#8217;s Sin are similar monsters. Error lives in shady, dark forest, which is (in these stories, anyway) almost always the site of shady, dark activities. Error&#8217;s cave resembles Plato’s Allegory of the Cave. The illusion effected by Archimago, who discovers a fictitious Una to the Red-cross Knight in the embraces of a young &#8216;squire, seems to be imitated from the deceptions carried on in the enchanted castle of Atlanta, where many of the guests are impos&#8217;d upon by false representations of the persons of their friends or mistresses; and more particularly from that passage where Orlando, after having been cheated with the appearance of a fictitious Angelica, is made to hear her cry out for his assistance, as if some villain was ravishing her. By “A shadie grove”,&nbsp;the wood of Error, Spenser shadows forth the danger surrounding the mind that escapes from the bondage of Roman authority and thinks for itself. The description of the wood is an imitation of Ariosto&#8217;sOrlando Furioso, i, 37, Chaucer&#8217;s&nbsp;Assembly of Foules, 176, and Tasso&#8217;s&nbsp;Jerusalem Delivered, iii, 75. Morley sees in this grove an allegory of man&#8217;s life, the trees symbolizing trade, pleasure, youth, etc. Imitation was an important aspect of Spenser’s poetic theory, but in his attempt to prove he was superior to his poetic ancestors. The Faerie Queene does much more than copy its originals, Spenser takes his borrowed matter and makes it his own, weaving each thread of allusion into a much larger framework, where it cannot be isolated or understood without reference to its context within the poem, and within the literary world of the late 16th century. By combining so many elements and styles, he creates something that cannot be described as purely Virgilian, Homeric, or Ovidian, but uniquely Spenserian, a plural voice intertwined with his own ambitions and experiences.</p>



<h3>BIBLICAL ALLUSION:</h3>



<p>It is impossible to quantify the collective impact that the Holy Bible has had on literature since its creation thousands of years ago. Throughout all six of The Faerie Queene’s books and the two Cantos of Mutabilitie, the Bible appears to be the foremost of those sources. Northrop Frye calls the first book of The Faerie Queene “the closest following of the Biblical quest-Romance theme in English Literature”. While the New Testament seems to have influenced the overarching themes and allegories present in Spenser’s The Faerie Queene , specific allusions are most frequently drawn from the Old Testament . Book I The first virtue Spenser tackles is holiness, exhibited through the adventures of the Redcrosse Knight against Archimago, an evil sorcerer. Multiple incidents in this first book can be traced to the first book of the Bible, Genesis. The first part of the Legend of Holiness parallels events in the Bible which preceded Christ&#8217;s birth suggesting that on another level, the history of the knight&#8217;s quest is also the entire history of mankind from the Fall in the Garden of Eden to the restoration of Man in the heavenly Jerusalem. As the poem later reveals, Una’s parents, the king and queen are the king and queen of Eden and like Adam and Eve, they have been expelled from their kingdom. “Red-crosse” is symbolically associated with Jesus Christ in Christianity so Red Cross knight resembles Jesus who helps to restore the fall of mankind. Spenser adjusts the biblical pattern to incorporate a political dimension to the meaning wherein the Kingdom of Eden represents an ideal state of England which existed in the past but which has been oppressed and wasted by its European Catholic enemies and awaits restoration by Una, a figure who functions as a type of Queen Elizabeth. The initial enemy that Redcrosse encounters is a dragon hybrid named Error, much like the original antagonist in Genesis — that is, a serpent with legs. This dragon is meant to evoke both “the serpent, was suttiller then euery beast of the fielde” (Gen 3:1) and Eve, who convinced Adam to eat the forbidden fruit, for Spenser describes it as, “Halfe like a serpent horribly displaide, / But th’ other halfe did womans shape retaine” (I.i.14.7–8). Spenser brilliantly ties together a direct reference to the two characters in Genesis who were responsible for the fall of man with an image from classical mythology. Like Satan, Errour is a composite of the two tempters of .Adam&#8211; the serpent and Eve. Errour&#8217;s &#8220;huge long taile in knots and many boughtes upwound,/ Pointed with mortall sting&#8221;(1.1.15) associates her with the labyrinth of the wandering wood itself and with the wandering Adam and Eve after their exile from the garden. The &#8220;mortall sting&#8221; suggests a second consequence of the Fall, death (&#8220;For as in Adam all die,,18). Also like the wood, Errour is an enemy of light and therefore an enemy of God, &#8220;For light she hated as the deadly bale&#8221; (1.1.16). Moreover, Errour&#8217;s scattered brood which suck up &#8220;their dying mother&#8217;s blood&#8221; (1.1.25) is an emblem of the self-defeating nature of sin. But finally God and Redcrosse both triumph over their serpentine adversaries, and end up removing a part of the foes’ bodies—Redcrosse “raft her hatefull head” (I.i.24.8) while God removes the snake’s legs, saying: “vpon thy belly shalt thou go” (Gen 3:14). In addition to detailing the fall of man, Genesis has a number of narratives that involve mistaken identities—Spenser borrows this idea to introduce the primary antagonist of The Faerie Queene, Archimago. As Redcrosse is wandering through the woods, he comes upon a man who seems to be a “godly father” (I.i.33.9) and decides to spend the night with him. In later cantos, Duessa is introduced as the virtuous Una’s malicious doppelganger, and Archimago disguises himself as Redcrosse (I.ii.11.1–2, 9). There are numerous examples in Genesis when characters put on the guise of another person to achieve desired ends. A few instances include when Jacob tricks his blind father into thinking he is Esau (Gen 28:6–40), Tamar posing as the temple prostitute (Gen 38:14–15), and Joseph’s pretending not to know his brothers when he is a vizier of Egypt (Gen 42:7–8). Spenser&#8217;s Christian knight is accompanied by a lady whose appearance also recalls a number of biblical associations. She is riding &#8220;upon a lowly Asse&#8221; which suggests the humility of Christ. Her whiteness is that of Truth and Faith and the &#8220;milke white lambe&#8221; (1.1.4) connects her with the innocence of the sacrificial lamb of John 1: 29. 5. In Revelation, “a great multitude&#8230; stoode before the throne, and before the lambe, clothed with long whyte garmentes” (7:9)—this lamb represents Jesus. Una, the purest character in the poem, carries with her “a milke white lambe&#8230; So pure and innocent” (I.i.4.9– 5.1), suggesting that Christ is with her. The Faerie Queene is a poem so obviously influenced by the Bible and Biblical ties, however, run deeper than just the “holiness” theme of Book One and the arrant holiness of the Bible. Spenser takes many narratives from Genesis, modifies them, and creates a world for Redcrosse. Often Spenser borrows the framework and not the actual events of a narrative, instead changing details of the stories for the effect of juxtaposition, or simply to fit The Faerie Queene’s plot. Spenser draws on Genesis narratives such as the fall of man. Equally important is the New Testament, in which the knights’ quests embody concepts from the epistles and Revelation. The actions of both Redcrosse parallel those of Jesus.</p>



<h3>MYTHS:</h3>



<p>In the first stanza of the poem Spenser begs for help from “holy virgin chiefe of nine” which&nbsp;refers to Clio, the muse of history though Spenser should have invoked Calliope, the muse of poetry. In many other stanza’s of book 1’s canto 1 and 2 Spenser refers to many other greek mythological characters, such as- “impe of highest jove” refers to&nbsp;Cupid, the god of love, and son of Jupiter and Venus. “triumphant mart” refers to&nbsp;Mars, the god of war. “Phoebus lampe” refers to&nbsp;Apollo, the sun-god. “blacke Plutoes griesly Dame” refers to&nbsp;Proserpine, the queen of darkness;&nbsp;Great Gorgon,&nbsp;Demogorgon, whose name might not be uttered, a magician who had power over the spirits of the lower world. The poet is here imitating the Latin poets Lucan and Statius. According to greek mythology “Cocytus”,&nbsp;the river of wailing, and&nbsp;“Styx”,&nbsp;the river of hate both exists in Hades. In classical mythology Tethys, goddess of&nbsp;the ocean, is the daughter of Uranus (heaven) and Gaea (earth), and the wife of Oceanus and Cynthia is&nbsp;the goddess of moon. “Fayre Venus” refers to&nbsp;the daughter of Jupiter, or Zeus, and the sea-nymph Dione. She is the same as Aphrodite, the Greek goddess of love and beauty. “the Graces” refers to&nbsp;Euphrosyne, Aglaia, and Thalia, daughters of Zeus and Aphrodite. “freshest Flora”,&nbsp;the goddess of flowers, typified spring. “faire Hesperus” is&nbsp;the evening star; “the rosy-fingred Morning” refers to Aurora, the goddess of the dawn, is borrowed from Homer, Hesiod, and other ancient poets. “aged Tithones,&nbsp;son of Laomedon, King of Troy. Aurora conferred upon him immortality without youth, hence the epithet &#8220;aged.&#8221; “Titan” is the sun-god in the Roman myths. “Proteus” is a sea-god who was endowed with the power of prophecy. He could change himself into any shape in order to avoid having to prophesy. (Homer,&nbsp;Odyssey, iv, 366&nbsp;seq., and Vergil,&nbsp;Georgics, iv, 387). A situation in Book I is brought about by the use of a device common in classical mythology, the use of a false dream. One such instance is found in the Iliad. Zeus sent a baneful dream to Agamemnon in order to bid him call to arms the Achaians with all speed to take the city of the Trojans. Zeus&#8217; purpose was to bring grief upon both the Trojans and Danaans through stubborn fights. Working after this manner, Spenser has a false dream sent to the Red Crosse Knight. The purpose ofthe dream is the separation of the Red Crosse Knight and Una in order to lure the Red Crosse Knight into certain dangerous adventures into which he can easily be led as he lacks the wisdom Una supplies him in dangerous situations. This dream is achieved through the magic of Archimago who by the means of his black art creates two sprites, one, whom he sends as his messenger to the Underworld where he is in league with evil mythological characters. He selects Morpheus, the Greek god of sleep to prepare the bad dream. This dream, portraying Una as the most infamous of women, is to horrify the Red Crosse Knight so that he will desert her. To make the dream real, Archimago uses the second sprite to impersonate Una. The illusion created thus is successful and the separation of the Red Crosse Knight and Una&#8217;s achieved. In the portrayal of the Greek God Morpheus, Spenser to show his drowsiness has the sprite threaten him with the &#8220;dreaded name of Hecate&#8221; goddess of the Underworld, sometimes identified with Proserpina and sometimes with Diana. Archimago sent the spirits to “A fit false dream, that can delude the sleeper&#8217;s sent.&#8221; (I. I. 43.)</p>



<h3>Dedication:</h3>



<p>The dedicatory page of the 1590 edition of Spenser&#8217;s&nbsp;Faerie Queene, reading: &#8220;To the most mightie and magnificent Empresse Elizabeth, by the grace of god, Queene of England, France and Ireland Defender of the Faith &amp;c.&#8221; The poem is dedicated to&nbsp;Elizabeth I&nbsp;who is represented in the poem as the Faerie Queene Gloriana. Poetic structure: The Faerie Queene&nbsp;was written in&nbsp;Spenserian stanza, which was created specifically for&nbsp;The Faerie Queene. In this style, there are nine iambic lines – the first eight of them five footed and the ninth a hexameter – which form &#8220;interlocking quatrains and a final couplet&#8221;.&nbsp;The rhyme pattern is ABABBCBCC. Over two thousand stanzas were written for the 1590Faerie Queene.</p>



<h3>What is Chivalry?</h3>



<p>Chivalry is the generic term for the knightly system of the Middle Ages and for virtues and qualities it inspired in its followers. The word evolved from terms such as chevalier (French), caballero (Spanish), and cavaliere (Italian), all meaning a warrior who fought on horseback. The term came to mean so much more during medieval times. The definition of Chivalry can be described as a term often related to medieval institution of knighthood referring to the codes of conduct, including courtly love, adhered to by Medieval knights with gallant knightly values including honor, bravery, courteousness and honesty. Chivalry was the honor code of the knight. An important part of chivalry was to show respect and gallantry towards women. The Code of Chivalry was an important part of the society and lives of people who lived during the Medieval times and era. The Code of Chivalry was admired and understood by all. A knight was expected to have not only the strength and skills to face combat in the violent era of the Middle Ages but was also expected to temper this aggressive side of a knight with a chivalrous side to his nature. There was not an authentic Code of Chivalry as such &#8211; it was a moral system which went beyond rules of combat and introduced the concept of Chivalrous conduct &#8211; qualities idealized by knighthood, such as bravery, courtesy, honor, and gallantry toward women. Chivalry toward Women &#8211; The Knight in Shining Armor Chivalry was the honor code of the knight and great importance was placed on courtesy towards women leading to the concept of a &#8216;Knight in Shining armor. In modern times the terms chivalry and chivalrous are used to describe courteous behavior, especially that of men towards women. The Code of Chivalry and Courtly Love The Code of Chivalry was combined with the romance of Courtly Love which was practised during the Medieval times and era. There were strict rules of courtly love and the art of Courtly Love was practised by the members of the royal courts across Europe during Medieval times. Surprisingly the romance, rules and art of Medieval Courtly Love together with the code of chivalry allowed knights and ladies to show their admiration for each other regardless of their marital state. It was a perfectly acceptable and common occurrence for a married lady to give a token to a knight of her choice to be worn during a Medieval tournament. Courtly love was acceptable as long as the rules relating to chastity and fidelity were strictly adhered to. There were rules which governed Medieval Courtly Love but sometimes the parties, who started their relationship with such elements of Medieval Courtly Love, would become deeply involved. A famous example of a relationship which was stirred by romantic Medieval Courtly Love and romance is described in the Legend of King Arthur, and the Knights of the Round Table, where his Queen, Guinevere fell in love with Sir Lancelot. Many illicit court romances were fuelled by the practise and art of Medieval Courtly Love. The Romantic Legend of King Arthur The romantic legend of King Arthur was fuelled by the Troubadours, jongleurs and Minstrels of the Medieval era. The stories of the valiant King Arthur, great knights, Camelot, chivalrous deeds, great battles and fair ladies were spread from court to court all over Europe by the troubadours. The image of King Arthur and the Knights of the Round Table took on the the clothes and fashion of the Medieval era. Jousting in tournaments were also incorporated. Fiction was again turning into fact. And we now have an answer as to why we associate King Arthur with the Medieval Kings.<br></p>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/2019/04/17/farie-queene-written-by-edmund-spenser/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
		<item>
		<title>Le Belle Dame sans Merci (French: &#8220;The Beautiful Lady Without Mercy&#8221;[1] )</title>
		<link>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/2019/04/17/le-belle-dame-sans-merci-french-the-beautiful-lady-without-mercy1/</link>
				<comments>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/2019/04/17/le-belle-dame-sans-merci-french-the-beautiful-lady-without-mercy1/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2019 10:21:59 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ayan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/?p=111</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[Rhyme Scheme and Meter: &#8220;La Belle Dame Sans Merci&#8221; is divided into twelve four-line stanzas, called quatrains. Each of those quatrains rhymes according to an ABCB pattern. In each stanza, the meter of the first three lines is iambic tetrameter. In this format, a line contains four feet (four pairs &#8230;]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h3>Rhyme Scheme and Meter:</h3>



<p>&#8220;La Belle Dame Sans Merci&#8221; is divided into twelve four-line stanzas, called quatrains. Each of those quatrains rhymes according to an ABCB pattern. In each stanza, the meter of the first three lines is iambic tetrameter. In this format, a line contains four feet (four pairs of syllables), with the stress falling on the first syllable in each pair. The first two lines of the poem demonstrate this metric pattern. The meter of the last line of each stanza is usually in iambic dimeter: In this format, a line contains two feet (two pairs of syllables), with the stress falling on the first syllable in each pair. &#8220;La Belle Dame sans Merci&#8221; (French: &#8220;The Beautiful Lady Without Mercy&#8221;[1] ) is a ballad written by the English poet John Keats. The poem is considered an English classic, stereotypical to other of Keats&#8217; works. It avoids simplicity of interpretation despite simplicity of structure. Keats uses the so-called ballad stanza, a quatrain in alternating iambic tetrameter and trimeter lines, with a simple ABCB rhyme scheme, the poem is nonetheless full of enigmas, and has been the subject of numerous interpretations. Keats uses a number of the stylistic characteristics of the ballad, such as simplicity of language, repetition, and absence of details; like some of the old ballads, it deals with the supernatural. Analysis: The title translates as, ‘The beautiful lady without mercy’, introducing the enchanting but cruel lady in the poem. This creates an ominous tone right from the beginning as this is not what the reader might traditionally expect from a courtly ballad. We can see this foreboding tone continue right from the first stanza of the poem. The speaker’s question suggests that the knight is &#8220;Alone and palely loitering&#8221; while the reference to the &#8220;wither’d’ plants&#8221; and the &#8220;lack of birdsong&#8221; suggests the lonely, desolate surroundings. The speaker uses words such as &#8220;haggard&#8221; and &#8220;woe-begone&#8221; to describe the knight which highlights how deathly and drawn he looks. The flower imagery used also emphasises how pale and haggard the knight looks. For example, the metaphor, &#8220;I see a lily on thy brow&#8221; conveys his paleness. The lily is also the flower associated with death and therefore contributes to the deathly feel of the poem. The rose metaphor, also in the third stanza, &#8220;And on thy cheek a fading rose/ Fast withereth too&#8221;, suggests that the colour has left his cheek and that his beauty (often represented by a rose) has withered. The knight himself begins his story in the fourth stanza, beginning with a description of the &#8220;beautiful lady&#8221; of the title. This idealistic description is characteristic of the Romantic era. She is described as, &#8220;Full beautiful&#8221; and&#8221;a faery’s child&#8221;, creating an enchanting and mysterious image. We begin to get an impression of her seductive nature from the line, &#8220;And her eyes were wild.&#8221; The knight describes how he is totally enthralled by this lady, so much that he &#8220;nothing else saw all day long&#8221;. There is a suggestion of supernatural enchantment when he mentions that she sang, &#8220;a faery’s song&#8221;. The world he describes sounds remote and captivating as he lists the &#8220;relish sweet, And honey wild, and manna dew&#8221;; there is a sense that she is enchanting him with exotic foods. &#8220;Manna&#8221; is the food that the Jewish scriptures say that the Israelites ate when they were wandering around the desert after Moses freed them from slavery in Egypt. It&#8217;s supposed to be food from heaven, so this word makes the fairy lady seem supernatural, if not actually divine. The otherworldliness is emphasized further when he describes how the lady spoke in &#8220;language strange&#8221;. In contrast with this infatuation however, Keats introduces a hint of sadness in the eighth stanza when the beautiful lady &#8220;wept, and sigh’d full sore&#8221;. This could be interpreted as being part of her seduction or is she herself doomed to capture young knights and spirit them away. In this setting, the delicate, fleeting nature of the lady’s feelings suddenly erupts with her tears, which the knight tries to soothe with his kisses that shut her “wild wild eyes”—words that suggest he has fallen in love with a creature that he cannot possess. Repetition of the word &#8220;Wild&#8221; emphasises her enchanting eyes as well as the knight’s obsession with her; this repetition also reflects the oral nature of the ballad and the ability of the form to keep the reader engaged. It is the lady who lulls the knight to sleep, however. In stanzas nine to eleven, he is engulfed in a dream of kings and princes who are pale (as he is at the beginning of the poem) and who warn him that he has become enslaved by the beautiful lady without mercy. When he awakes, the knight finds himself on the &#8220;cold hill’s side”, feeling the deathlike cold of his dream and looking like the sad figure the speaker first encountered. Coming full circle in stanza twelve, the knight notes that his experience with the lady is why he remains in this bleak setting, alone and feeling that he has lost the love of this beautiful figure that haunts and blights not only his life but also the world in which he finds himself. The final stanza completes the description of the knight’s appearance to the unknown speaker. Keats sets his simple story of love and death in a bleak wintry landscape that is appropriate to it: &#8220;The sedge has wither&#8217;d from the lake / And no birds sing!&#8221; The repetition of these two lines, with minor variations, as the concluding lines of the poem emphasizes the fate of the unfortunate knight and neatly encloses the poem in a frame by bringing it back to its beginning. This deceptively simple tale written in a ballad style, featuring short lines and romantic longings, evokes the human yearning for an eternal, imperishable love, a bond that outlasts death and that conquers mortality. To lose the lady is tantamount to a kind of death for the knight. Thus, John Keats uses the medieval setting as a kind of allegory, a symbolic representation of what love represents. To the lover, the beloved is a fairy creature usually associated with perfection and with the desire to do good and to protect the loved one. The knight is at the mercy of his love, meaning both the lady and the knight’s feelings for the lady. When she withdraws her love, she is portrayed as without mercy. The heat of passion vanishes, and this is why the knight feels cold and why the world itself seems frigid.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/2019/04/17/le-belle-dame-sans-merci-french-the-beautiful-lady-without-mercy1/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Black Cat Written By Edgar Allan Poe</title>
		<link>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/2019/04/17/the-black-cat-written-by-edgar-allan-poe/</link>
				<comments>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/2019/04/17/the-black-cat-written-by-edgar-allan-poe/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2019 10:17:24 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Salsabil Hayat]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/?p=102</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[“The Black Cat” is a short story by Edgar Allan Poe (1809-1849) which was published in 1843.More than any of Poe&#8217;s stories, &#8220;The Black Cat&#8221; illustrates best the capacity of the human mind to observe its own deterioration and the ability of the mind to comment upon its own destruction &#8230;]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h5>“The Black Cat” is a short story by Edgar Allan Poe (1809-1849) which was published in 1843.More than any of Poe&#8217;s stories, &#8220;The Black Cat&#8221; illustrates best the capacity of the human mind to observe its own deterioration and the ability of the mind to comment upon its own destruction without being able to objectively halt that deterioration. It is a study of the psychology of guilt, in the story a murderer carefully conceals his crime and believes himself unassailable, but eventually breaks down and reveals himself, impelled by a nagging reminder of his guilt.</h5>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<p>Poe believed that a man was capable at any time of undergoing a complete and total reversal of personality and of falling into a state of madness at any moment. The story opens in the cell of a prisoner the day before he is to be executed by hanging where he was writing down the details of this experience, which led to his imprisonment and scheduled execution. The narrator describes himself as a caring and loving man, who and whose wife was very fond of animals. Over the years, the narrator’s disposition changed. He became prey to certain wicked human emotions as &#8220;Intemperance&#8221; and &#8220;Perverseness,&#8221; and these feelings of excess and cruelty began to consume him. The narrator then began to drink alcohol heavily and stay out during the nighttime, staggering home very late. He became “more moody, more irritable, more regardless of the feelings of others&#8221;, started shouting at his wife, and even struck her at times. He mistreated all of his pets except his most loving cat Pluto. In time, however, he even started to mistreat the cat. And one night, so enraged did the narrator become that he withdrew a pocket knife and cut out one of the cat’s eyes. The next morning, though he was horrified by what he had done the spirit of “perverseness” overcame him again with the course of time &#8211; this time, with an unfathomable longing of the soul to &#8220;offer violence . . . to do wrong for the wrong&#8217;s sake only.&#8221; Suddenly one morning, he hanged the cat from the limb of a tree, but even while doing it, tears streamed down his face. He is ashamed of his perversity because he knows that the cat had loved him and had given him no reason to hang it. What he did was an act of pure perversity. Though he was becoming mad day by day, he tried to explain everything with logic. That night, after the cruel deed was executed, his house burned to the ground. Being a rational and analytical person, the narrator refuses to see a connection between his perverse atrocity of killing the cat and the disaster that consumed his house. Peculiarly, on the single wall that did not fall in the fire is an image of a gigantic cat with a rope around its neck. The narrator explains the phenomenon away with scientific reasons. The battle in the narrator’s mind between delusion and reality rages at this point. He tries desperately to explain what he sees with rational thought, but his mind is already infected with superstition and his explanations begin to sound far-fetched and somewhat insane. In the story we see his guilt make him belief in the reincarnation of the cat. After some months he found another cat which looking exactly the same to Pluto and this one also became a great favorite to him and his wife. The narrator&#8217;s perversity, however, caused him to soon change, and the cat&#8217;s fondness for them began to disgust him. It was at this time that he began to loathe the cat. What increased his loathing of the new cat was that it had, like Pluto, one of its eyes missing. In the mind of the narrator, this cat was obviously a reincarnation of Pluto. After a time, the narrator develops an absolute dread of the cat. When he discovers the white splash on its breast, which at first was rather indefinite he was terrified. Here we can assume that the change occurs within the mind of the mad man in the same way that he considers this beast to be a reincarnation of the original Pluto. He was so much terrified that he just wanted to get rid of the cat at any cost. One day, in a fit of rage, the narrator raised an axe to strike at the creature, but he “buried the axe in” his wife’s head. The narrator realizes that he must get rid of the body and finally &#8220;wall it up in the cellar”. Afterward, he looked for the cat, “for I had, at length, firmly resolved to put it to death.” But it had disappeared–apparently in fear of his wrath. That night, even with the weight of murder on his mind, he slept soundly. After all, there was no cat to irritate him. After three days, the narrator decided that the &#8220;monster of a cat&#8221; had disappeared forever; he was now able to sleep soundly in spite of the foul deed that he had done. The narrator says, “My happiness was supreme”. This lack of guilt is certainly a change from what his feelings were at the beginning of the story. His over confidence caused his final downfall. On the fourth day, a party of police unexpectedly arrives to inspect the premises. The narrator delights in the fact that he has so cleverly and so completely concealed his horrible crime that he welcomes an inspection of the premises. When the police was about to leave, the narrator – pleased at his cleverness and his ability to handle the police – began to talk too much. In an act of insane bravado, he raps so heavily upon the bricks that entombed his wife, that to his abject terror, a &#8220;voice from within the tomb&#8221; answered. At first, it was a muffled and broken cry, but then it swelled into an &#8220;utterly anomalous and inhuman . . . might have arisen only out of hell&#8221; The police immediately began to tear down the brick wall, and they discover the rotting corpse of the narrator&#8217;s wife and, standing upon her decayed head was the &#8220;hideous beast whose craft had seduced me into murder . . . I had walled the monster up within the tomb.&#8221; The final irony, of course, is that the cat which he had come to so despise — the cat that might have been the reincarnation of Pluto — serves as a figure of retribution against the murderer. ************************************************************************************* **Short story in the horror genre that focuses on the psyche of the narrator. Poe was one of the developers of the short story as a literary genre. He defined a short story as a narrative prose work that (1) is short enough to be read in one sitting, (2) takes place in one locale on a single day, (or even in a few hours), (3) centers on a single line of action, and (4) maintains a single mood. Every word or phrase should contribute to the theme and the mood. *** The supernatural elements of &#8220;The Black Cat&#8221; leave open the question of how much is real, how much can be rationally explained, and how much is a product of the narrator&#8217;s imagination. Pluto&#8217;s possible magical significance is first noted by the wife, who states that black cats are said to be witches in disguise, although her kind treatment of Pluto indicates that she does not put much faith in this particular superstition. The narrator explicitly dismisses this viewpoint, but the superstition flavors his entire story. When he observes the image of the cat on the wall, he describes it as gigantic; he previously described Pluto as fairly large, but whether the size of the image is an expression of the paranormal or simply a product of his frightened imagination is difficult to say. The other popular notion relevant to this story is the belief that a cat has nine lives; this superstition becomes a part of the story when the second black cat is believed to be a reincarnation of the dead Pluto with only one slight but horrible modification — the imprint of the gallows on its breast but we have no evidence that the narrator is observing anything more than the twisting of his own mind. ***&#8221;The Black Cat&#8221; is in many ways a moral tale that deals with the tension between love and hate and that warns of the dangers of alcohol, a substance to which Poe himself was addicted for much of his life. The narrator appears at first to love both his wife and his pets, but by the end of the story his fondness has turned to neglect, spite, and even hatred, particularly for Pluto and his successor. Although Poe does not provide a solid explanation for the narrator&#8217;s encroaching loss of sanity, perhaps suggesting that madness might happen at any time to any person, the narrator admits the role of alcohol in his behavior. In addition, the arrival of the second cat is closely related to his alcoholism, since he first finds the cat in a seedy drinking establishment. The second cat ultimately serves as the facilitator of justice when it reveals the corpse&#8217;s hiding place at the end of the tale, and its initial appearance on top of a hogshead of gin or rum emphasizes its moral purpose.&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/2019/04/17/the-black-cat-written-by-edgar-allan-poe/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Dream Of The Rood</title>
		<link>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/2019/04/17/the-dream-of-the-rood/</link>
				<comments>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/2019/04/17/the-dream-of-the-rood/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2019 10:11:25 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ayan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/?p=100</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[The Dream of the Rood, one of the few surviving pieces of Anglo-Saxon literature, is a vital reference for the ambiguous culture of England&#8217;s early ancestors. It is one of the earliest Christian poems in Old English literature, and one of the earliest Christian poems in all of Anglo-Saxon literature. &#8230;]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h3 style="text-align:center">The Dream of the Rood, one of the few surviving pieces of Anglo-Saxon literature, is a vital reference for the ambiguous culture of England&#8217;s early ancestors.</h3>



<p>It is one of the earliest Christian poems in Old English literature, and one of the earliest Christian poems in all of Anglo-Saxon literature. Both its author and its date of composition are unknown and surfaced in a late tenth-century manuscript found in Vercelli, which is in northern Italy. Argued as one of the oldest pieces of Old English Literature,&nbsp;The Dream of the Rood&nbsp;effectively embodies the blended culture, moral code, and religious values of its unknown author. In the poem the narrator recalls a vision he received in a dream, where he encounters the rood on which Christ was crucified.</p>



<p>***The authorship of the poem is lost to us. The names of Caedmon and Cynewulf have been proposed as authors, in part because they are two of the very few Anglo-Saxon Christian writers from the period whose names are known. Caedmon is known because the Venerable Bede talks about him in his history of the English church, written in the seventh century A.D., and it has been argued that no one else at the time could have written the rood poem.</p>



<p>***This is a story about someone who has a dream about the holy cross. He talks about how he sees a tree and there are angels that are looking over it. He says that the tree is surely not a tree made for sinful people but for someone with the Holy Spirit. The tree/cross is decked with gold and very ornate showing its importance. The dreamer acknowledges that the tree was once drenched with blood but is now adorned with treasure. The next part of the story says that the tree starts speaking. It tells its own story about its experience through the crucifixion. It tells how it was pierced with nails. It makes it seem like it had a choice to be a cross or not. It said that it had to follow Gods&#8217; word. The cross tells of how they mocked not just Jesus but both of them. The cross tells of how he was wounded with arrows when the roman soldiers took Jesus down from it. They laid him down, he went cold. Everything around the cross went quiet as the soldiers left. The last paragraph talks about how the cross now searches for glory. It doesn&#8217;t have many friends now because they are all in heaven. He says he will wait till the day the lord comes back. He will come back to get his cross. Until then he will dwell in glory. He finishes saying that everyone will rejoice when “Almighty God” comes back home.</p>



<p>Paganism vs. Christianity in “The Dream of the Rood”: The &#8220;Dream of the Rood&#8221; is certainly a very old English poem, perhaps one of the very first composed in our language at all. The version we have of it is found in a medieval Italian text called the Vercelli Book, which was written about the 10th century A.D. The poem brings, more than a thousand years earlier, a reverse image &#8211; that of a tree becoming the Cross. As the first example of Anglo-Saxon religious poetry in the form of a dream vision the poem is not just a conventional rendering of Christian dogmas in verse. The poem details the crucifixion of Christ from the viewpoint of the Rood.&nbsp;Christianity of course heavily influences the poem and there are&nbsp;also some paganistic elements as well.&nbsp; The rood&#8217;s dictation, steeped with references to both Pagan and Christian culture, implies the subservient relationship he shared with Christ as that of a lord and thane. Furthermore, the crucifixion scene is metaphorically illustrated as a battle and elevates both Christ and the rood to the warrior status reminiscent of Anglo-Saxon heroes. This contradictory concept of Christ as a self-sacrificing victim, yet fearless warrior king, coupled with the conflicting references to Pagan and Christian culture demonstrate the blended perspective of the poem&#8217;s author. Within the context of the poem, the clash between the newly emerging society of ecclesiastical ethics and Pagan tradition of heroism and warfare is evident.</p>



<p>The Dream of the&nbsp;Rood is first and foremost a Christian piece. J. A. Burrow has praised it as &#8220;one of the first and one of the most successful treatments in English of the theme of the Crucifixion.&#8221; The poem takes the form of a dream, which the narrator, an unnamed man, relates to the reader. While the term &#8220;rood&#8221; refers to a cross, the dream is really about a tree that has been fashioned into a cross. Specifically, the tree has been turned into the cross used to crucify Christ, and feels immense sorrow and pain at what he has become which he relates to the dreamer in a long passage. The poem&nbsp;details the death and resurrection of Christ, the triumph over sin and evil,&nbsp;and stresses the importance of the Rood or Cross as we know it.&nbsp; The death and resurrection of&nbsp;Christ is very important in the Christian religion, it is&nbsp;because Christ gave his life “to set free mankind” and to forgive mankind of their sins.</p>



<p>When Christ rose again on the third day he made his triumph over sin and evil and proved he was the true Son of God.&nbsp;The Rood shares this triumph with Christ over death. Instead of&nbsp;fearing death they face it refusing to bend or bow. The Bible says not to fear for the Lord is with you and&nbsp;the account of the Rood&nbsp;enforces this idea. Another Bible verse that enforces the idea of&nbsp;triumph over death in this poem is&nbsp;“He who believes in me will live, even though he dies; and whoever lives and believes in me will&nbsp;never die” (John 11:25-26). When Christ dies,</p>



<h3>“All of creation wept,/keened the king&#8217;s death./ Christ was on the cross”.</h3>



<p>The poem is heavily laden with references to pagan culture. For instance the dreamer recalls the cross telling him about the crucifixion as if it were a battle. Bernard F. Huppé has summarized this view, remarking that &#8220;the Crucifixion is pictured as a battle and both Christ and the Cross as warriors, whose deaths are victories, and whose burials are preludes to the triumph of their Resurrections.&#8221; Additionally, the poem presents Christ as a heroic warrior. The narrator regards the willing sacrifice of Christ&#8217;s life as a triumph and embodies Christ with the courage, honor, and might of a traditional Anglo-Saxon king. While the rod explains that he could have easily &#8220;felled all the enemies&#8221; for Christ, Christ instead willingly, “eager to mount the gallows,/ Unafraid in the sight of manu:/ He would set free mankind”. With this action Christ proves himself a heroic being, determined to carry out God&#8217;s divine plan, even if it means losing his life in the process.</p>



<p>Like all Anglo-Saxon heroes, Christ submits himself to the winds of fate and gains immorality. The rood, like a burial mound, becomes a symbol of Christ&#8217;s triumph. Christ can also be seen as an Anglo-Saxton warrior lord, who&nbsp;is served by his thanes, especially on the cross and who rewards them at the feast of glory in Heaven. Christ is addressed here as “mankind’s brave king”, “Bringer of Victory”, “most high Prince”, “Prince of Glory”. Thus, the crucifixion of Christ is a victory because Christ could have fought his enemies, but he chose to die on the cross.</p>



<p>Throughout the poem there are strong suggestions of a lord/ thane relationship between Christ and the rood, where the rood is presented as a selfless retainer of Christ. The relationship is subtlety suggested when the dreamer witnesses the rood began to bleed on the right side as Christ had, implying the inseparable connection between lord and thane. This bond is later solidified when the rood and Christ are depicted in battle together and the rood obediently follows the desires of his lord, recalling that he did &#8220;I dared not break or bend aside/ against God’s will&#8221;. At the conclusion of the poem, the narrator himself accepts this lord/thane relationship with Christ. Just as the lords of ancient times presented thanes with treasures for their service, the poet regards this vision of the gold-enameled cross as a gift from God and is thus bound by the Anglo-Saxon code of conduct to serve Christ. Besides this image as Christ as a warrior king, the very idea of a talking tree is incredibly animisitc, referring to the way in which pagan elements incorporate spirits and other fantastical elements of nature.&nbsp;Paganism puts a great emphasis on the spiritual elements that embody various things in Mother Nature. Specifically in the poem, this belief that natural objects possess a spirit or spiritual elements urges the reader recognize the tree as an object of worship.&nbsp;When christs followers found the tree or rood they “grit me with gold and silver”. The tree&#8217;s triumph over death is thus celebrated by adorning the cross with gold and jewels, in a way worshipping the&nbsp;tree as if it were an idol, remembering the days of pagan&#8217;s faith in idolatry. The cross goes on to tell us that it was richly adorned with &#8220;treasure,&#8221; which was gold, as a warrior would expect, and the blood of Jesus, which a theologian would expect. Often in Anglo-Saxon&#8217;s heroic literature, weapons are given personalities. The physical image of a cross is very similar to that of a sword, which was often given personalities. Famous swords such as Hrunting, belonging to Beowulf, became symbols of power and kingship. Similarly the Rood becomes the symbol of Christ’s kingly power. This would explain the extravagant appearance of the Rood, as powerful swords were personified as loyal retainers entitled to receive treasures as the symbol of their service. This takes the form of gold and gems with which they are adorned. This also gives us the combined images of the Rood as Christ’s retainer, and Christ as the Ring-Giver, “great king” or lord. One can note that in this story, the cross suffers along with Christ, even bearing wounds from arrows. While the Gospel story has no arrows, the Saxons would have assumed that any great battle must have had them in plenty, and the cross had to take its fair share of the warrior&#8217;s suffering. But, of course, in the Christian story, Christ rises from the dead. And just like a brave and victorious king who shares the spoils of war with his loyal thanes, so too Christ the king shares his victory with the cross, who has served him as a fellow warrior in combat. The Cross then goes on to address everyone, as fellow warriors in the great struggle. He tells us, doubtless imagining us sitting around the council&#8217;s hearth fire, drinking our mead and listening to the scops, or the bards sing the ballads of our ancestors. The cross says to the listening warriors,</p>



<h3>“Now I command you, my beloved warrior,/ that you tell this vision to men,/reveal in words that it is the tree of glory,/ on which Almighty God suffered/ for mankind&#8217;s many sins/ and Adam&#8217;s deeds of old”.</h3>



<p>Despite these strong pagan elements, the very&nbsp;nature of&nbsp;The Dream of the Rood&nbsp;is based upon Christian belief. The entire poem deals with the passion, death and resurrection of Christ&nbsp;acting as a triumph over sin and evil. Here the dreamer realizes that Christ&#8217;s death was not some victory in battle, but was in fact a way in which human salvation&nbsp;was secured.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Personifying an inanimate object is typical of the medieval tradition in which swords, mead and the like are personified in riddles. Riddles were typically told in the mead hall as entertainment for the thanes. By using the cross as a narrator, the poet uses a common medieval technique that would help to appease and entertain the audience.In addition to the cross&#8217;s warrior-like description, he also possesses another Anglo-Saxon quality. He possesses the ability to boast. The author personified the cross itself to speak about the death and resurrection of Jesus. As &#8220;The Dream of the Rood&#8217;s&#8221; many deviations from the biblical account of the crucifixion suggest, the image of Christ in the Middle Ages emphasized the salvation Christ brought to mankind by presenting him as a triumphant warrior over sin. The depiction of Christ receiving a Beowulf-type burial rather than the type of burial recorded in the gospels shows how the image of Christ in the Middle Ages had been adapted from the image of Christ recorded in the gospels. Rather than presenting Christ as a lamb or a passive participant in the universal plan for redemption, the poet presents Christ as a martyred hero, an image that reflects the preeminent values of the early medieval society. The appearance of the cross and the way in which the cross&#8217;s experiences are told are strikingly different from traditional Christian ideas. Instead, the description in the poem is rather Anglo-Saxon.In the Christian tradition that preaches humility and deemphasizes riches, this description of the cross does not seem to fit. To the mind of the Anglo-Saxon on the other hand, this would sound appealing. Blood, arrows, gashes, treasure, and gold would all spark an interest to the Anglo-Saxon culture. The poem creates a warrior-like Lamb of God and a strongly medieval afterlife.Although the ideas of humility and selflessness may not fit neatly into Anglo-Saxon society, this poem finds a way to convince the audience of Christian values. A dream vision or visio is a literary device in which a dream or vision is recounted as having revealed knowledge or a truth that is not available to the dreamer or visionary in a normal waking state. Anonymous, The Dream of the Rood – the guide in Dream of the Rood is the Cross on which Christ was crucified. This genre typically follows a structure whereby a narrator recounts his experience of falling asleep, dreaming, and waking, and the story is often an allegory. The dream, which forms the subject of the poem, is prompted by events in his waking life that are referred to early in the poem. In the course of the dream, the narrator, often with the aid of a guide, is offered perspectives that provide potential resolutions to his waking concerns.The Dream of the Rood has three parts: the Dreamer’s account of his vision of the Cross, the Rood’s monologue describing the Crucifixion, and the Dreamer’s resolution to seek the salvation of the Cross.In the end, the Dreamer is renewed with hope and vows to seek again the glorious Rood. The dream-vision convention was widely used in European literature from late Latin times until the 15th century. The dream vision uses strong, virile images of Christ in order to reach members of the Anglo-Saxon warrior culture, who valued strength above humility. This may have been a deliberate strategy to convert pagans to Christianity. The Dream of the Rood draws with astonishing creativity at the secular heroic ethos. &#8220;The Dream of the Cross&#8221; has been called &#8220;one of the great religious poems of the English language,&#8221; the finest dream-allegory in Anglo-Saxon as well as one of the earliest extant versions of the medieval dream-vision, and hailed as a portrayal of Christ &#8220;as a truly heroic Germanic warrior with his disciples as his loyal comitatus.&#8217; &#8220;The Dream of the Cross&#8221; is therefore a powerful argument for the spiritual qualities of honor, truth, and courage which marked the Anglo-Saxon mind before Christianity and the spiritual qualities of mercy, justice, and love after Christianity had spread. Cross has faith &amp; is like a thane. The Dream of the Rood also provides a valuable window into early Christian Anglo-Saxon England/Britain. Like most Old English poetry, it is written in alliterative verse. Preserved in the 10th century Vercelli Book discovered, in 1822, northern Italy the poem may be as old as the 8th century Ruthwell Cross, a large stone carving dating to the early eighth century. Eighteen verses of The Dream of the Rood were carved into the cross in runic lettering and it is considered one of the oldest works of Old English literature. The Dream of the Rood and the gospel tales of the crucifixion are separated not only by time, but by culture, language and depiction of the nature of Christ. The most obvious difference is that it is told from the POV of the cross whilst the biblical gospels are described by the apostles. In spite of this, there are clear parallels between the 2 accounts of crucifixion &#8211; both detail Christ&#8217;s death as a triumph of good over evil and redemption of mankind as a positive. Thus, these accounts follow the same event, but employ widely different methods of narration to explore greater themes.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/2019/04/17/the-dream-of-the-rood/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
		<item>
		<title>Way of the World Written By William Congreve</title>
		<link>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/2019/04/17/way-of-the-world-written-by-william-congreve/</link>
				<comments>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/2019/04/17/way-of-the-world-written-by-william-congreve/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2019 10:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ayan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/?p=98</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[Restoration Comedy of Manners: “The Way of the World” which is written by William Congreve (1670-1729), remiered in 1700, is the most apposite example of comedy of manners with its witty dialogues between the characters, criticism of the upper class people’s manners and also satiric and effective scenes and proviso &#8230;]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h5>Restoration Comedy of Manners: “The Way of the World” which is written by William Congreve (1670-1729), remiered in 1700, is the most apposite example of comedy of manners with its witty dialogues between the characters, criticism of the upper class people’s manners and also satiric and effective scenes and proviso scene that ends in a lyrical celebration of unity. This comedy contains almost all the qualities which we find in a Restoration comedy and thus representing the peak and the perfection of this type of comedy. It presents a vast vista of contemporary social morality and principles and maintains a satirical tone from the beginning to the end. It gives us valuable information about the sophisticated class of society in England at that time.</h5>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<p>The Comedy of Manners also termed as a Restoration comedy is a witty and cerebral form of dramatic comedy that depicts and often satirizes the manners and affectations of a contemporary society. “The comedy of manners deals with the relations and intrigues of men and women living in a sophisticated upper-class society, and relies for comic effect in large part on the wit and sparkle of the dialogue—often in the form of repartee, a witty conversational give-and-take which constitutes a kind of verbal fencingmatch—as well as on the violations of social standards and decorum by would be wits, jealous husbands, conniving rivals, and foppish dandies”. The themes of the Restoration comedy of manners are love, marriage, adulterous relationships amours and legacy conflicts; and the characters generally include would be wits, jealous husbands, conniving rivals foppish dandies, fanatics, fools, imitators of French customs, conceited wits, and flirts. These plays are often centered around love and adultery and include gossip, eavesdropping, and scheming. Conversation is often witty and ironic. The Restoration period was an age of loose morals and, and was devoid of moral values. The Way of the World contains this current through the illicit love and adulterous relations – e.g. relation between Fainall and Mrs. Marwood, between Mirabell, the hero, and Mrs. Fainal. Mirabell married Mrs. Fainall off to Fainal, being afraid of her being pregnant. Fainall’s illicit relationship with Mrs. Marwood having been exposed, Fainall faces the situation fearlessly and shamelessly: “If it must all come out, why let ‘them know it; it’s but the way of the world.” Even Mrs. Marwood and Lady Wishfort secretly loved Mirabell. Unhappy conjugal life can be treated as another characteristic of the time which is expressed through the relation between Mr. and Mrs. Fainall. One of them feels uneasy in the presence of another. Mrs. Fainall expresses her uneasiness in St ames’s park in the presence of her husband- “He turned sort upon me unaware, and had almost overcome me.” The institution of marriage was always held to ridicule. Both husbands and wives openly expressed their dissatisfaction of their spouses. Mrs. wood says, “I have done hating &#8217;em, and am now come to despise &#8217;em;&nbsp;the next thing I have to do is eternally to forget em.” The Way of The World also exposes the worldliness and greed of the young men of the time. Mercenary motives led them to seek rich heiresses in marriage. Mr. Fainall marries Mrs. Fainall, a widow, for her property. Mirabell does not want to marry Millament without her property. This mercenary tendency led them to intrigue which was the order of the day in social and domestic life. Mirabell, in order to obtain Milament with her whole legacy, pretends to woo Lady Wishfort. He marries off his servant to Wishfort’s maid and sends his servant as Sir Roland to Lady Wishfort so that the servant can make a marriage contact with the lady. Even Sir Wilfull, an exception to other characters of the play, joins the web of intrigues in the play. Moreover, Fainall makes the legacy-conflict deeper through his cruel condition to Lady Wishfort. In The Way of The World, we are acquainted with the vanities, affectations and fashions of the time. Mirrabell satirically remarks in the proviso scene on women’s fondness of wearing masks, going to the theatre with or without their husbands’ knowledge, idle gossip, slandering the absent friends etc. In her contact with Mirabell, Millament proves her habit of late rising, contemplation in solitude general laziness etc. She says, “I’ll ye abed in a morning as long as I please.” Mirabell also ridicules pregnant women’s wearing tight dresses in order to maintain their figure. Moreover, intelligent women like Millament allowed a crowd of admirers to a school of fools to gather around them in order to show their demand and worth. Millament’s vanity is revealed in causing her lover pain to have a sense of power: “One’s cruelty is one’s power.” Above all, Lady Wishfort, a higher class fashionable lady, seeks a husband in her age of fifty five. Mirabell ridicules her saying, “The good lady would marry anything that resembled a men.” And the make up and dressing up of women of the society is expressed in the speech of the footman about Lady Wishfort of the house- “I cannot swear to her face in a morning, before she is dressed.” The upper class people could give up anything only to maintain/save the family name and fame. Lady Wishfort wants to conceal the scandal of her daughter by any means. She says, “I’ll compound, I’ll give up all, myself and my all, my niece and her all- anything, everything for composition.” The Way of The World brings before us witty Restoration ladies and gentlemen even their servants and fools are witty. As a result, the dialogue is throughout witty which is something unrealistic.. Therefore the play, like other plays of its kind, is called an ‘artificial’ comedy. From Footman’s speech we know about frequent changing of servantsin that society. Asked by Willfull about how long he is here, the Footman replies, “A week sir: longer than anybody in the house, except my lady’s woman.” Complicated plot construction is also regarded as a quality of comedy of manners. In this play, the five acts contain sixty five scenes in total, and there are very complicated relations among the characters. Such as, Mirabell, the hero is loved by Millament, Mrs. Fainall, Mrs. Marwood, and even Lady Wishfort secretly. He had a relation with Mrs. Fainall, onced tried to woo Lady wishfort and now trying to marry Millament. Witty dialogue and repartee are perhaps the most important features of the Comedy of Manners. The best example of a scene of witty dialogue is the &#8216;proviso&#8217; scene in which Millamant specifies her conditions before she agrees to accept Mirabell as her husband and he in turn also states his conditions. Millamant insists, “Let us be as strange as if we had been married a great while, and as well-bred as if we were not married at all.” To sum up, the whole plot of the play revolves around the issues of adultery, marriage and fortune hunting and mocks the society, or in other ways lift up society for scrutiny, which could cause negative or positive results. Congreve’s writing style shows both intelligence and sympathy with his creativity of the characters fixed with the aspects of the Restoration Comedy. The selfish, absurd and unbalanced manners of the characters are criticises clearly with the ironic and satiric usage of Congreve. Also, the importance of witty dialogues cannot be disregarded as the absolute proofs of the comedy of manners. The discussion above makes it very much clear that The Way of the World presents a faithful picture of the manners of the restoration period and the eighteenth century social picture. Though when the play was first performed in 1700 it was not a huge success, but later on it was realized that the play is a classic example of comedy of manners and Congreve’s “magnum opus” or master work. Major Themes: The themes of The way of the world: After Charles II revived theater in 1660, a new kind of comedy, the comedy of manners exploded onto the English drama scene and remained the preferred style of theater for the rest of the century. The aim of these plays was to mock society, or rather to hold it up for scrutiny by those very people whose social world was being characterized on stage. The Way of the World reflects Congreve&#8217;s personal view of Restoration society and city life, full of its artificiality, rigidity, and formality. As is typical of Restoration Theater, this play&#8217;s main themes are centered around that of marriage, money, love, social reputation, artificiality in manners, law, legacy conflicts, conspiracy, double status, adulterous relationships amours; and the characters generally include would be wits, jealous husbands, conniving rivals and foppish dandies. Love a la Mode: Certainly, the play can be seen as a dramatic presentation of varieties of love in the England of the year 1700. Central is the delicate handling of the love game as played by Mirabell and Millamant. They represent the ideal of the Restoration attitude, intense yet balanced, their love based on mutual esteem with no surrender of individuality. Contrasted with it are Mirabell&#8217;s earlier and quite ambiguous love affair with Mrs. Fainall; the illicit love of Fainall and Mrs. Marwood, presumably passionate, but wholly without mutual trust; the spurious court young Witwoud pays to Millamant; the direct and somewhat coarse approach of Sir Wilfull; and, at the opposite extreme completely, the aging and undignified longings of Lady Wishfort, vain, unrealistic, over-eager, desperate, and a little pathetic. Love and Money: Money is a distinct concern for several of the characters in Congreve’s play. In the world whose way is presented here, love and money are values to be taken into account at all times. The sentiment of love itself is not enough to build a romantic relationship on or to protect family bonds. Money is actually an indispensible ingredient of love as money provides for a comfortable life, which then allows one to enjoy one’s love. The dominant Restoration attitude was that while love is important, but it must not obscure the importance of money. Mirabell’s love for Millament is genuine, but he will not let the ‘moiety’ of her fortune go. The sincerity of Mirabell&#8217;s love does not make him lose sight of the importance of Millamant&#8217;s fortune. Fainall marries for money to support an illicit love; apparently the thought of marrying Mrs. Marwood without adequate money is unthinkable. Money is Lady Wishfort&#8217;s sole hold over her child and her ward. Even the marriage of the servants itself is also a testament to this theme. It is built on a promise of a handsome sum of money. This is the world&#8217;s way. Love without money is an impossible sentimental dream, although money often corrupts what love there is. Marriage: Marriages are central thematic concerns as Mirabell’s machinations are fuelled by his desire to marry Millamant, and Fainall uses his marriage to try to extract money from his mother-in-law, Lady Wishfort. The state of marriage is depicted as simultaneously desirable, and yet to be avoided as a trap should be. These aspects of marriage are used to comic effect, but the play ends finally with a warning against falsehood in the marriage bed and so reminds the readers and the audience that it is dishonesty in marriage rather than marriage that has been questioned here. Dishonesty and disloyalty is depicted as a core feature of marriage in Way of the world. Mrs. Fainall had a relationship with Mirabel but married Fainall to avoid rumours or unwanted pregnancy… Mr. Fiannal and Mrs. Marwood has an adulterous relationship though Mr. Fainall is married to … Marriage was dependent on the social status, money and power that the individuals possessed. It was unheard of, at that time, to marry solely for love. The highly contrived plot of&nbsp;The Way of the World&nbsp;reflects these preoccupations with money and status. Even though Mirabell loves Millament, he is unwilling to let go of her inheritance. The entire plot is designed to allow the two to marry with Lady Wishfort’s permission. While marriages are important economic contracts, they are also convenient vehicles for protecting social reputations. Mrs. Fainall has made such a marriage, which is socially acceptable and even expected, as long as the pretense of civility is maintained. Jungle of High Intrigue: In this play everyone is engaged in intrigue: Mirabell intrigues to gain consent to his marriage from Lady Wishfort, and this involves intrigue within intrigue, for he does not trust Waitwell. Fainall intrigues in turn. Everyone is involved in one or the other of these schemes&#8211;Mrs. Fainall, Mrs. Marwood, and the servants. Even Lady Wishfort in her willingness to marry Sir Rowland has a devious purpose&#8211;revenge on Mirabell. When Mrs. Fainall married her husband, that was part of an intrigue, as was his marriage to her. And as we see in the play, victory goes to Mirabell, not because of his virtue, but simply because he is the most successful intriguer. Social Etiquette and Reputation: &#8220;Why do we daily commit disagreeable and dangerous actions? To save that idol, reputation.&#8221; (Act II, Scene II) A Comedy of Manners is named as such to call attention to one of its most central themes &#8211; manners, or social etiquette, and the comedy that can ensue because of the importance, especially to the upper class during the Restoration, of preserving one&#8217;s position in society. In the climax of the play, the actions and reactions largely stop being concerned with love or even money, and what Lady Wishfort seems to fear most is a loss of good reputation for herself and her daughter. Much of the demonstrated love seen in the show &#8211; for example, Witwoud and Petulant&#8217;s love for Ms. Millamant &#8211; is done purely in hopes of raising one&#8217;s reputation. Fun is made of social etiquette especially in the acting of Petulant, Sir Wilfull, and Sir Rowland, three characters that to varying degrees are unable to live up to upper class standards, but must try to put on a show for others. Friendship: Same-gender and opposite gender friendships are called into question in this play, as it is said and demonstrated that none of these relationships is particularly strong or trusting. The women-women and men-men pairings, though originally posing as friends, join schemes against one another based mostly on money and reputation. As for women-men pairings, we do not see many in the play that are not based on either mutual love or the love of one and disdain of the other. Certainly, friendship is as falsely fashionable and tactical as anything else in the play. Social Convention: Congreve&#8217;s ‘‘comedy of manners’’ takes the fashionable or conventional social behavior of the time as the principle subject of satire. Conflicts that arise between and among characters are prompted by affected and artificial social mores, especially with respect to relationships between the sexes. Social pretenses and plot complications abound in&nbsp;The Way of the World. Women are compelled to act coyly and to dissemble in courtship; couples deceive one another in marriage; friends are double-dealing, and conquests have more to do with dowries and convenience than love. All moral principle is risked for the sake of reputation and money. However, what makes the action comic is the subterfuge. What one says is hardly ever what one really thinks or means. To judge by appearances, for example, no one could be happier in his marriage than Fainall, who in reality disdains his wife and is carrying on an adulterous affair with his wife&#8217;s close friend. Congreve intimates that, in fashionable society at the turn of the eighteenth century, it is crucial to preserve the outer trappings of beauty, wit, and sophistication no matter how egregious one&#8217;s actions and words might prove. Significance of the title: “The Way of the World” which is written by William Congreve (1670-1729), premiered in 1700, is the most apposite example of comedy of manners with its witty dialogues between the characters, criticism of the upper class people’s manners and also satiric and effective scenes that ends in a lyrical celebration of unity. The title of this play is significant because it points to one of the major themes of the play &#8212; it sort of signals to us what the play is about. The way of the word generally means, the manner in which people typically behave or things typically happen. The play is a &#8220;comedy of manners&#8221; in which the playwright pokes fun at the social customs and values of his time.&nbsp; He makes fun of marriages and dowries and he makes fun of the way men and women behave towards each other. The title of the play is rightly suitable, first, it is inspired by the then social period during which the play was originally performed. Secondly, as a comedy of manners, it makes fun of human follies and silly social behaviors. But some critics also suggest that The Way of the World&nbsp;points to the ‘way’ the hero and heroine should adopt in order to come out of the grip of the fashionable society. The entire play is set in London and this urban setting keeps especial importance. It basically represents metropolitan aristocratic society and ridiculed people for their lack of sophistication.&nbsp; The Act 1 begins in the chocolate house where many people come to enjoy. Similarly, Act II begins in St. James Park. The park suggests something as freedom. This is a public place where basically fashionable people use to go to exchange their heart and to be free. Act III, too, begins in Lady Wishforts’ house, but the very scene is in the toilet. Remaining inside the toilet, Lady Wishfort is talking to Peg in serious matters. It clearly shows that how restoration people take the serious things lightly. In Act IV, lady Wishfort and Foible are talking the arrival of Sir Roland. Lady Wishfort orders to Foible to arrange the things in order and she also asks for dancer and musician if he (Sir Roland) wants to entertain. It is the showy nature of the Restoration period (people). Because people like Lady Wishfort is very much concerned on how to perceive and impress man in his first visit. As a result, she talks how to sit, how to walk, how to talk in front of him. She says, ‘I will walk from the door upon his entrance and how do I look?’ These some events clearly show that how the restoration people are very pedantic in their fashion and outer appearance. In the same way, in another scene, Millamant talks with her lover Mirabell that she does not like to be familiar or found, she rejects to go any park not she plays together, even after the marriage, and she wants to be like unmarried one. Likewise, she wants liberty to write letters, to receive letters, to talk with a lover, to have dinner with him and to bring him in her dressing room. Even her husband must knock the door, before entering the room if her lover is inside the room. These are the general condition she talks with Mirabell before getting married. This is what actually the Restoration period was. In the play male characters are pursuing women. We can take the instance of Mirabell, Witwood, Petuland and Fainall who seem adulterous and deceptive. It was because fashionable to court a young and beautiful woman in the contemporary society. In the play, everyone plots against everyone and deceives everyone. And the play begins, we know that Mirabell pretends to love Lady Wishfort in order to be touched with Millamant, the single heir of the property. Mr. Finall, the fortune hunter is also committed to get Millament’s fortune at hand. We find the characters in disguise and they do their best to be what they are not. To pretend to be what one is not is the way of the world. So, the title itself suggests the manner of Restoration urban aristocrats. The very title of the play,&nbsp;The Way of the World&nbsp;points to the ‘way’ the hero and heroine should adopt in order to come out of the grip of the fashionable society. The whole story is an illustration of the process, by following which Mirabell and Millament seek a resolution, that is, to gain their own world by using and manipulating the existing social norms, through the winding lanes of that society. Congreve constructed the plot of the play accordingly with this aim in mind. One can discern a definite pattern in the movement of the play. At the beginning of the play, Mirabell is trying to shape up a situation so that he can win both hands of Millament and her estate from Lady Wishfort. He has married his servant, Waitwell off to Lady Wishfort’s maid, Foible and plans to have Waitwell disguise himself as a noble man, court, and marry Lady Wishfort. Then Mirabell would blackmail her by threatening to disclose that she has married a servant and would offer her to release her if she will let him marry Millament plus the estate. But Mrs. Marwood discovers the plan and tells Lady Wishfort. Mrs. Marwood also tells Fainwall of his wife, Mrs. Fainwall’s former relationship with Mirabell. From all these Fainwall plans to blackmail Lady Wishfort by threatening to reveal all unless she signs over to him not only his wife’s but also Millament’s estate and even the conversation of Lady Wishfort’s own estate after her death. As the action of the play gets momentum and the plot becomes more and more complicated, Congreve loads the stage by introducing confusing figures like Mr. Wilful Witwood. While it adds to the comedy of the play, it complicates the plot further. However, certain hidden facts of the past are revealed through the conversations of the characters: for instance, Mrs. Marwood’s desire for Mirabell, Mrs. Marwood’s relationship with Fainall, Mirabell’s past affair with Mrs. Fainall etc. Congreve measures these secrets slowly person by person, until the final revelation in Act V, where all pretences are destroyed Mr. Fainall’s and Mirabell’s revelations, and the bringing out from a black box of the deed renders Mr. Fainall powerless. The complexities and complications are, however, deliberate on Congreve’s part; for he wanted to present his Restoration audience a play that can coincide artistically with the artificialities and complexities in the human affairs of the period. The chief aim of the dramatist is to demonstrate “the way of the world”. Following this way Mirabell and Millament, through their own peculiar balance of wit and generosity of spirit, reduce the bumbling Witwood and Mr. Fainall to the same level of false wit. Thus the pair dramatise the true wit that is carefully and symmetrically defined through their opposition. They are aware of the fact that they are making compromises in their marriage. Mirabell says, “…I like her with all her faults: nay, I like her for her faults…They are now grown familiar to me as my own frailties…” And Millament charmingly declares, “Well, if Mirabell should not make a good husband, I am lost thing—find I love him violently.” These confidences do not prevent their own chances for honesty in marriage. In the Proviso Scene they arrange an agreement for their marriage. The reason is obvious: that is, marriage is a social contract that would enable them to rise above the cant and hypocrisy that surround them. The triumph of the play is in the emergence of lovers who through a balance of intense affection and cool self-knowledge achieve an equilibrium that frees them from the world’s power. As the title of the play&nbsp;The Way of the World&nbsp;suggests, they have assimilated the rational lucidity of skeptical rake so that they can use the world and reject its demands. Beneath the surface of proper English society are layers of deceit, greed, vanity, pretension, silliness, desire for revenge, and indecorous romance. Congreve&#8217;s sharp wit pierces this surface to reveal society as it is, with all its faults, foibles, follies, and bitter rivalries. He shows the reader “the way of the world.&#8221; Proviso Scene: It was quite common for Restoration comedies to have Proviso scenes, that is, scenes where the hero and heroine define a set of rules which they would like the other to follow in order to facilitate a balanced relationship. In a way they are setting the parameters of an equal marriage. the Proviso Scene is one of the most remarkable aspects of William Congreve&#8217;s(1670-1729) &#8220;The Way of the World&#8221;(1700). In Act 4 of The Way of the World, couple Mirabell and Millamont find themselves in a battle of wit as they discuss the terms of their marriage. This scene, called the proviso scene, gives important insight into Mirabell and Millamont&#8217;s relationship. The terms of both characters illustrate their concerns and fears for their future marriage. The scene is a pure comedy with brilliant display of wit by both of them, but, above all, provides instructions which have serious dimensions in the context of the society. Mirabell and Millament both are well-acquainted with the ‘Way of the World’, and see the Provisos as a way to a stable future, where both can have their freedom. They lay down a set of rules which they would like the other to comply to. Mirabell sounds patronising and sententious, yet his provisos reveal that he is not altogether insensitive. He reveals his thoughtfulness and his foresight when he declares that he wants no intrigue in his house, and if that condition is fulfilled, he would agree to be a “tractable and complying husband”. Mirabell and Millamant’s marriage will be different from the other relationships in the play because it would be based on mutual respect and love. The nature of their provisos shows their genuine love for each other.&nbsp;They will forge a new Way of the World with their marriage and the Provisos each sets for the other shows that they genuinely care for each other and are keen to be faithful in their marriage. Through this scene appears very funny but it is a serious comment on the degradation of conjugal relations. The conditions as set down by the two lovers, confirm the sincerity of their motives and their wish to live a married life which was different from others. Both of them accept each other&#8217;s conditions. It is a guideline or memorandum of understanding between a husband and a wife, which would enable them to spend a happy married life. According to Millamant’s first condition, she wants equal amount of love and affection on the part of her would husband throughout her life. Behind her conditions one can notice the pitiable condition of a wife after marriage. Just before marriage when men and women are lovers they declare full support and love for each other but things take a turn when they marry each other. So Millamant appears anxious because of this reason and that is why she puts this condition. Again, Millamant says that she hates those lovers who do not take proper care of their beloveds. She further wants that her husband must be a loyal and good natured man.&nbsp; Millamants conditions shows that they will compromise but won’t bid adieu to their individuality and freedom. Millamant says to Mirabell that she wants her liberty after her marriage; she informs Mirabell that she can&#8217;t forgo her independence, she says, &#8220;My dear liberty, shall I leave thee? My faithful solitude, my darling contemplation, must I bid you adiue?&#8230; My morning, thoughts, agreeable wakings, indolent slumbers, all ye douceurs, &#8230; Adieu &#8212; I can&#8217;t do it, &#8217;tis more than impossible.&#8221; She also adds that &#8220;I will lie a bed in a morning as long as I please&#8221;. Even she demands that she can receive and pay visits and letters to anyone she pleases. In the former scene one can see that Mr. and Mrs. Fainal, though don’t have any love or care for each other, addresses each other as “my dear”, “my soul” in public just to go with the flow of social decorum. But Millament criticizes this public “show off” and informs that she would not like to be addressed by such names as “wife, spouse, my dear, joy, jewel, love, sweet-heart; and the rest of that nauseous can, in which men and their wives are so fulsomely familiar.” Moreover, they will continue to present a decorous appearance in public. In other words, after marriage they maintain certain distance and reserve between them. She says, “Let us be as strange as if we had been marry’d a great while; and as well bred as if we are not marry’d at all.” Each of Mirabell’s provisos begin with its item: first, the general principle, “that your Acquaintance be general”, then specific instructions, “no she-friend to screen her affairs”, no fop to take her to the theatre secretly, and an illustration of the forbidden behaviour, “to wheedle you a fop-scrambling to the play in a mask”. Nevertheless, Mirabell denounces the use of tight dresses during pregnancy by women, and he forbids the use of alcoholic drinks. Though at first his conditions seems patronizing gradually they proved his genuine love and concern for her. The conditions are stated by both parties in a spirit of fun and gaiety, but the fact remained that both are striving to arrive at some kind of mutual understanding. Mirabells conditions also mocked some flaws in social practices. In that century women used to put a heavy makeup to hide their flaws which consume a lot of time and energy. Act III scene I is a nice example of this practice. But Mirabell criticizes this practice by one of his conditions. He says Millamant should not use the artificial things to cover her real appearance. On that time people used to pay visits to one another and specially women used to criticize one another behind one’s back. One of Mirabell’s “article”s was, Millamant should not be in company of any woman who has a notorious background or who indulges in scandalous activities. This condition revels the practice of backbiting of the people of that time. In Congreve’s “The Way of the World” Congreve seems to come to realise the importance for providing an ideal pair of man and woman, ideal in the sense that the pair could be taken for models in the life-style of the period. In fact, it serves as an excellent medium through which Congreve conveys his message to his readers. The lovers negotiate in this scene for a mutual private happiness within the confines of a rigid and demanding social context and they establish their relationship upon the possibility of such reconciliation. They manage to be sincere in a world full of pretence and their love is in any case true love.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/2019/04/17/way-of-the-world-written-by-william-congreve/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Bachelor’s Complaint of the Behavior of Married People By Charles Lamb’s</title>
		<link>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/2019/04/17/a-bachelors-complaint-of-the-behavior-of-married-people-by-charles-lambs/</link>
				<comments>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/2019/04/17/a-bachelors-complaint-of-the-behavior-of-married-people-by-charles-lambs/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2019 10:08:13 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ayan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/?p=88</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[“A Bachelor’s Complaint of the Behavior of Married People” was first published in 1823 in Charles Lamb’s (1775-1834) essay collection “Essays of Elia”. This essay has a mock serious or Pseudo serious tone and it is written in an argumentative style. Charles Lamb’s essay “A Bachelor’s Complaint of the Behavior &#8230;]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p class="has-drop-cap"> “A  Bachelor’s Complaint of the Behavior of Married People” was first published in 1823 in Charles Lamb’s (1775-1834) essay collection “Essays of Elia”. This essay has a mock serious or Pseudo serious tone and it is written in an argumentative style. Charles Lamb’s essay “A Bachelor’s Complaint of the Behavior of Married People” is just what the title suggests: it is indeed a bachelor’s complaint of the behavior of married People. Lamb emphasizes his single status in the start of the essay “As a single man” and in doing so, separates himself from the “Married People.” He talks about Married People as if they are despicable and offensive and gives both hypothetical and personal examples to back up his points. Married People set themselves apart in their own groups through their attitudes. They really do seem to be off in their own little world of love, and this is what Lamb dislikes. He believes that Married People “prefer one another to all the world” and openly flaunt it, thus offending singles such as Lamb by implying that they “are not the object of this preference”. Furthermore, Lamb believes that overall, singles are looked down on Married People are undoubtedly more favored and knowledgeable. The main complaint that Lamb is making throughout the whole essay is the Married People’s attitudes and how they demonstrate their status. Towards the end of the essay, Lamb brings up the subject of children and how they also contribute to the Married People’s attitudes. He brings out all the negative aspects of children and emphasizes them by listing them continuously with dashes as separation. By using the negative aspects of children, he furthers his disapproval of Married People and their actions.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<p>Lamb’s purpose in writing “A Bachelor’s Complaint of the Behavior of Married People” is to bring to attention the attitudes of Married People. He wishes for his audience to realize how Married People subconsciously flaunt themselves in their love, offending those who are single. Ultimately, he hopes that Married People will bring themselves to correct their mistakes and be more considerate towards others. He structures his argument by stating his main reason for decrying Married People is because he believes them to be overly involved with each other and their love that they disregard and “perk it up in the faces of [singles] so shamelessly”. From this claim, Lamb offers personal anecdotes as well as hypothetical situations that illustrate and support his points. He concludes his essay stating that although he despises their attitudes, he is still willing to “forgive their jealousy and dispense with toying with their brats” but thinks it “unreasonable to be called upon to love them”. Through Lamb’s willingness to forgive these people whom he disapproves of, he is seen to be credible with good values and his readers are more inclined to believe his words and work to correct the attitudes of Married People. The structure of Lamb’s argument logically appeals to his readers, for it flows and flows and clarifies his points through examples. However, Lamb fails to address any possible counterarguments. His argument addresses only the negative aspects of Married People, but surely there are positive sides as well. By failing to address and disprove these possibilities, Lamb leaves room for doubt. Despite this, his argument stands strong, the examples he gives are cogent and, through his personal anecdotes, he is able to establish a connection with the audience. He also appeals emotionally especially to the singles, for he is a bachelor himself. The injustice that he sometimes feels can appeal to others who have felt the same way. Although there are some flaws in his arguments, they are overlooked and undermined by his credibility and emotional appeal. Overall, “A Bachelor’s Complaint of the Behavior of Married People” is effectively portrayed through Lamb’s arguments and claims. His complaints are easy to understand because of the examples that he gives. He makes many good points about Married People, and most likely is able to persuade many readers of his views.<br></p>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/2019/04/17/a-bachelors-complaint-of-the-behavior-of-married-people-by-charles-lambs/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
		<item>
		<title>A River By Attipate Krishnaswami Ramanujan</title>
		<link>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/2019/04/17/a-river-by-attipate-krishnaswami-ramanujan/</link>
				<comments>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/2019/04/17/a-river-by-attipate-krishnaswami-ramanujan/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2019 09:45:55 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ayan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/?p=82</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[River is written by Attipate Krishnaswami Ramanujan who is known as one of the greatest modern poet of India. The tone of the poem is based on sarcasm and irony. The structure of the poem has been in paragraphs and single lines. There are four longer verse paragraphs and a &#8230;]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>River is written by Attipate Krishnaswami Ramanujan who is known as one of the greatest modern poet of India. The tone of the poem is based on sarcasm and irony. The structure of the poem has been in paragraphs and single lines. There are four longer verse paragraphs and a shorter one in the beginning. There are only two single isolated lines. This kind of structural arrangement contributes to the effect of irony. It also helps to grasp the main points clearly.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<p>“A River” is a realistic description of the river Vaikai which flows through the city of Madurai. The poem implicitly comments wryly on the lack of realism with which other poets have treated the same topic. The poet has compared and contrasted the attitudes of the old poets and those of the new poets to human suffering. He has come to the conclusion that both the groups of the poets are not sympathetic, rather indifferent to human sorrow and suffering. This kind of attitude makes their poetry weak and unappealing, dry and cheerless. In the first stanza, Madurai is described as a “city of temples and poets,” making it sound like a place of great spiritual significance and associating it also with creativity and beauty. Its poets, indeed, have often sung of “cities and temples”, thereby celebrating places of great importance. Yet no sooner does the speaker make Madurai sound like a mythic, magnificent location than he immediately complicates this impression. He reports that each summer the city’s river—a river that might itself symbolize power, vitality, and energy—“dries to a trickle” uncovering “sand ribs”. He details the underbelly of the river that stays hidden. Visible now, are the bits of “straw and women’s hair” that chokes the rusty gates of the dam and the bridges that are plastered over with ‘patches of repair’. This stanza closes with a complain that all the poets ‘‘only sang of the floods’’. In stanza two, the poet speaks of the river in flood in the rains. He was there once and saw what happened. The river in spate destroys everything in its wake from live-stock to houses to human life. This happens once a year and has been continuing for years in the same pattern. He notes the casual approach of the of the towns people. Anxiously they talk of the rising level of water and enumerate mechanically the ‘precise’ number of steps as the water brims over the bathing places. The flood water “carried off three village houses,/ one pregnant woman/ and a couple of cows/ named Gopi and Brinda.” Humor is presented in the names of the cows and this too, is an attack on the orthodoxy of Hinduism. While cows are given names, no one knows who the pregnant woman is nor are they concerned. The third stanza opens with a complain that new poets have no wit but to blindly copy their predecessors and “no one spoke/ in verse/ of the pregnant woman”. The poet imagines that she may have drowned with not one life in her but two—“twins in her” which kicked “at blank walls even before birth”. He is sarcastic about both the new poets and old poets who seize only the floods to write about and that too merely once a year but did not refer to all these miseries of the woman in their poetic creations. The final stanza the poet mentions that “the river has water enough/ to be poetic” but only “once a year”. Maybe the river is beautiful and charming but it takes a heavy toll on human lives. It only takes “half-hour” to destroy “three village houses”, and take away the lives of humans and animals. This is an unusual poem with many layers of meaning and is a commentary on the indifference of the old and modern poets to the ravages caused by the river in flood and the pain and suffering caused to humans.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/2019/04/17/a-river-by-attipate-krishnaswami-ramanujan/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
