4a48
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Anglo-Saxon &#8211; NotesOfLit</title>
	<atom:link href="https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/tag/anglo-saxon/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit</link>
	<description>A Site FIlled With Literary Notes</description>
	<lastBuildDate>
	Tue, 16 Apr 2019 21:39:10 +0000	</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.1.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/cropped-cropped-Logo-32x32-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Anglo-Saxon &#8211; NotesOfLit</title>
	<link>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>The Dream Of The Rood</title>
		<link>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/2019/04/16/the-dream-of-the-rood/</link>
				<comments>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/2019/04/16/the-dream-of-the-rood/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2019 21:39:10 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ayan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Old English literature]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Anglo-Saxon]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[earliest Christian poems]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/?p=60</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[The Dream of the Rood, one of the few surviving pieces of Anglo-Saxon literature, is a vital reference for the ambiguous culture of England&#8217;s early ancestors. It is one of the earliest Christian poems in Old English literature, and one of the earliest Christian poems in all of Anglo-Saxon literature. &#8230;]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h3>The Dream of the Rood, one of the few surviving pieces of Anglo-Saxon literature, is a vital reference for the ambiguous culture of England&#8217;s early ancestors.</h3>



<p>It is one of the earliest Christian poems in Old English literature, and one of the earliest Christian poems in all of Anglo-Saxon literature. Both its author and its date of composition are unknown and surfaced in a late tenth-century manuscript found in Vercelli, which is in northern Italy. Argued as one of the oldest pieces of Old English Literature,&nbsp;The Dream of the Rood&nbsp;effectively embodies the blended culture, moral code, and religious values of its unknown author. In the poem the narrator recalls a vision he received in a dream, where he encounters the rood on which Christ was crucified.</p>



<p>***The authorship of the poem is lost to us. The names of Caedmon and Cynewulf have been proposed as authors, in part because they are two of the very few Anglo-Saxon Christian writers from the period whose names are known. Caedmon is known because the Venerable Bede talks about him in his history of the English church, written in the seventh century A.D., and it has been argued that no one else at the time could have written the rood poem.</p>



<p>***This is a story about someone who has a dream about the holy cross. He talks about how he sees a tree and there are angels that are looking over it. He says that the tree is surely not a tree made for sinful people but for someone with the Holy Spirit. The tree/cross is decked with gold and very ornate showing its importance. The dreamer acknowledges that the tree was once drenched with blood but is now adorned with treasure. The next part of the story says that the tree starts speaking. It tells its own story about its experience through the crucifixion. It tells how it was pierced with nails. It makes it seem like it had a choice to be a cross or not. It said that it had to follow Gods&#8217; word. The cross tells of how they mocked not just Jesus but both of them. The cross tells of how he was wounded with arrows when the roman soldiers took Jesus down from it. They laid him down, he went cold. Everything around the cross went quiet as the soldiers left. The last paragraph talks about how the cross now searches for glory. It doesn&#8217;t have many friends now because they are all in heaven. He says he will wait till the day the lord comes back. He will come back to get his cross. Until then he will dwell in glory. He finishes saying that everyone will rejoice when “Almighty God” comes back home.</p>



<p>Paganism vs. Christianity in “The Dream of the Rood”: The &#8220;Dream of the Rood&#8221; is certainly a very old English poem, perhaps one of the very first composed in our language at all. The version we have of it is found in a medieval Italian text called the Vercelli Book, which was written about the 10th century A.D. The poem brings, more than a thousand years earlier, a reverse image &#8211; that of a tree becoming the Cross. As the first example of Anglo-Saxon religious poetry in the form of a dream vision the poem is not just a conventional rendering of Christian dogmas in verse. The poem details the crucifixion of Christ from the viewpoint of the Rood.&nbsp;Christianity of course heavily influences the poem and there are&nbsp;also some paganistic elements as well.&nbsp; The rood&#8217;s dictation, steeped with references to both Pagan and Christian culture, implies the subservient relationship he shared with Christ as that of a lord and thane. Furthermore, the crucifixion scene is metaphorically illustrated as a battle and elevates both Christ and the rood to the warrior status reminiscent of Anglo-Saxon heroes. This contradictory concept of Christ as a self-sacrificing victim, yet fearless warrior king, coupled with the conflicting references to Pagan and Christian culture demonstrate the blended perspective of the poem&#8217;s author. Within the context of the poem, the clash between the newly emerging society of ecclesiastical ethics and Pagan tradition of heroism and warfare is evident.</p>



<p>The Dream of the&nbsp;Rood is first and foremost a Christian piece. J. A. Burrow has praised it as &#8220;one of the first and one of the most successful treatments in English of the theme of the Crucifixion.&#8221; The poem takes the form of a dream, which the narrator, an unnamed man, relates to the reader. While the term &#8220;rood&#8221; refers to a cross, the dream is really about a tree that has been fashioned into a cross. Specifically, the tree has been turned into the cross used to crucify Christ, and feels immense sorrow and pain at what he has become which he relates to the dreamer in a long passage. The poem&nbsp;details the death and resurrection of Christ, the triumph over sin and evil,&nbsp;and stresses the importance of the Rood or Cross as we know it.&nbsp; The death and resurrection of&nbsp;Christ is very important in the Christian religion, it is&nbsp;because Christ gave his life “to set free mankind” and to forgive mankind of their sins.</p>



<p>When Christ rose again on the third day he made his triumph over sin and evil and proved he was the true Son of God.&nbsp;The Rood shares this triumph with Christ over death. Instead of&nbsp;fearing death they face it refusing to bend or bow. The Bible says not to fear for the Lord is with you and&nbsp;the account of the Rood&nbsp;enforces this idea. Another Bible verse that enforces the idea of&nbsp;triumph over death in this poem is&nbsp;“He who believes in me will live, even though he dies; and whoever lives and believes in me will&nbsp;never die” (John 11:25-26). When Christ dies,</p>



<h3 style="text-align:center">“All of creation wept,/keened the king&#8217;s death./ Christ was on the cross”.</h3>



<p>The poem is heavily laden with references to pagan culture. For instance the dreamer recalls the cross telling him about the crucifixion as if it were a battle. Bernard F. Huppé has summarized this view, remarking that &#8220;the Crucifixion is pictured as a battle and both Christ and the Cross as warriors, whose deaths are victories, and whose burials are preludes to the triumph of their Resurrections.&#8221; Additionally, the poem presents Christ as a heroic warrior. The narrator regards the willing sacrifice of Christ&#8217;s life as a triumph and embodies Christ with the courage, honor, and might of a traditional Anglo-Saxon king. While the rod explains that he could have easily &#8220;felled all the enemies&#8221; for Christ, Christ instead willingly, “eager to mount the gallows,/ Unafraid in the sight of manu:/ He would set free mankind”. With this action Christ proves himself a heroic being, determined to carry out God&#8217;s divine plan, even if it means losing his life in the process.</p>



<p>Like all Anglo-Saxon heroes, Christ submits himself to the winds of fate and gains immorality. The rood, like a burial mound, becomes a symbol of Christ&#8217;s triumph. Christ can also be seen as an Anglo-Saxton warrior lord, who&nbsp;is served by his thanes, especially on the cross and who rewards them at the feast of glory in Heaven. Christ is addressed here as “mankind’s brave king”, “Bringer of Victory”, “most high Prince”, “Prince of Glory”. Thus, the crucifixion of Christ is a victory because Christ could have fought his enemies, but he chose to die on the cross.</p>



<p>Throughout the poem there are strong suggestions of a lord/ thane relationship between Christ and the rood, where the rood is presented as a selfless retainer of Christ. The relationship is subtlety suggested when the dreamer witnesses the rood began to bleed on the right side as Christ had, implying the inseparable connection between lord and thane. This bond is later solidified when the rood and Christ are depicted in battle together and the rood obediently follows the desires of his lord, recalling that he did &#8220;I dared not break or bend aside/ against God’s will&#8221;. At the conclusion of the poem, the narrator himself accepts this lord/thane relationship with Christ. Just as the lords of ancient times presented thanes with treasures for their service, the poet regards this vision of the gold-enameled cross as a gift from God and is thus bound by the Anglo-Saxon code of conduct to serve Christ. Besides this image as Christ as a warrior king, the very idea of a talking tree is incredibly animisitc, referring to the way in which pagan elements incorporate spirits and other fantastical elements of nature.&nbsp;Paganism puts a great emphasis on the spiritual elements that embody various things in Mother Nature. Specifically in the poem, this belief that natural objects possess a spirit or spiritual elements urges the reader recognize the tree as an object of worship.&nbsp;When christs followers found the tree or rood they “grit me with gold and silver”. The tree&#8217;s triumph over death is thus celebrated by adorning the cross with gold and jewels, in a way worshipping the&nbsp;tree as if it were an idol, remembering the days of pagan&#8217;s faith in idolatry. The cross goes on to tell us that it was richly adorned with &#8220;treasure,&#8221; which was gold, as a warrior would expect, and the blood of Jesus, which a theologian would expect. Often in Anglo-Saxon&#8217;s heroic literature, weapons are given personalities. The physical image of a cross is very similar to that of a sword, which was often given personalities. Famous swords such as Hrunting, belonging to Beowulf, became symbols of power and kingship. Similarly the Rood becomes the symbol of Christ’s kingly power. This would explain the extravagant appearance of the Rood, as powerful swords were personified as loyal retainers entitled to receive treasures as the symbol of their service. This takes the form of gold and gems with which they are adorned. This also gives us the combined images of the Rood as Christ’s retainer, and Christ as the Ring-Giver, “great king” or lord. One can note that in this story, the cross suffers along with Christ, even bearing wounds from arrows. While the Gospel story has no arrows, the Saxons would have assumed that any great battle must have had them in plenty, and the cross had to take its fair share of the warrior&#8217;s suffering. But, of course, in the Christian story, Christ rises from the dead. And just like a brave and victorious king who shares the spoils of war with his loyal thanes, so too Christ the king shares his victory with the cross, who has served him as a fellow warrior in combat. The Cross then goes on to address everyone, as fellow warriors in the great struggle. He tells us, doubtless imagining us sitting around the council&#8217;s hearth fire, drinking our mead and listening to the scops, or the bards sing the ballads of our ancestors. The cross says to the listening warriors,</p>



<h3>“Now I command you, my beloved warrior,/ that you tell this vision to men,/reveal in words that it is the tree of glory,/ on which Almighty God suffered/ for mankind&#8217;s many sins/ and Adam&#8217;s deeds of old”.</h3>



<p>Despite these strong pagan elements, the very&nbsp;nature of&nbsp;The Dream of the Rood&nbsp;is based upon Christian belief. The entire poem deals with the passion, death and resurrection of Christ&nbsp;acting as a triumph over sin and evil. Here the dreamer realizes that Christ&#8217;s death was not some victory in battle, but was in fact a way in which human salvation&nbsp;was secured.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Personifying an inanimate object is typical of the medieval tradition in which swords, mead and the like are personified in riddles. Riddles were typically told in the mead hall as entertainment for the thanes. By using the cross as a narrator, the poet uses a common medieval technique that would help to appease and entertain the audience.In addition to the cross&#8217;s warrior-like description, he also possesses another Anglo-Saxon quality. He possesses the ability to boast. The author personified the cross itself to speak about the death and resurrection of Jesus. As &#8220;The Dream of the Rood&#8217;s&#8221; many deviations from the biblical account of the crucifixion suggest, the image of Christ in the Middle Ages emphasized the salvation Christ brought to mankind by presenting him as a triumphant warrior over sin. The depiction of Christ receiving a Beowulf-type burial rather than the type of burial recorded in the gospels shows how the image of Christ in the Middle Ages had been adapted from the image of Christ recorded in the gospels. Rather than presenting Christ as a lamb or a passive participant in the universal plan for redemption, the poet presents Christ as a martyred hero, an image that reflects the preeminent values of the early medieval society. The appearance of the cross and the way in which the cross&#8217;s experiences are told are strikingly different from traditional Christian ideas. Instead, the description in the poem is rather Anglo-Saxon.In the Christian tradition that preaches humility and deemphasizes riches, this description of the cross does not seem to fit. To the mind of the Anglo-Saxon on the other hand, this would sound appealing. Blood, arrows, gashes, treasure, and gold would all spark an interest to the Anglo-Saxon culture. The poem creates a warrior-like Lamb of God and a strongly medieval afterlife.Although the ideas of humility and selflessness may not fit neatly into Anglo-Saxon society, this poem finds a way to convince the audience of Christian values. A dream vision or visio is a literary device in which a dream or vision is recounted as having revealed knowledge or a truth that is not available to the dreamer or visionary in a normal waking state. Anonymous, The Dream of the Rood – the guide in Dream of the Rood is the Cross on which Christ was crucified. This genre typically follows a structure whereby a narrator recounts his experience of falling asleep, dreaming, and waking, and the story is often an allegory. The dream, which forms the subject of the poem, is prompted by events in his waking life that are referred to early in the poem. In the course of the dream, the narrator, often with the aid of a guide, is offered perspectives that provide potential resolutions to his waking concerns.The Dream of the Rood has three parts: the Dreamer’s account of his vision of the Cross, the Rood’s monologue describing the Crucifixion, and the Dreamer’s resolution to seek the salvation of the Cross.In the end, the Dreamer is renewed with hope and vows to seek again the glorious Rood. The dream-vision convention was widely used in European literature from late Latin times until the 15th century. The dream vision uses strong, virile images of Christ in order to reach members of the Anglo-Saxon warrior culture, who valued strength above humility. This may have been a deliberate strategy to convert pagans to Christianity. The Dream of the Rood draws with astonishing creativity at the secular heroic ethos. &#8220;The Dream of the Cross&#8221; has been called &#8220;one of the great religious poems of the English language,&#8221; the finest dream-allegory in Anglo-Saxon as well as one of the earliest extant versions of the medieval dream-vision, and hailed as a portrayal of Christ &#8220;as a truly heroic Germanic warrior with his disciples as his loyal comitatus.&#8217; &#8220;The Dream of the Cross&#8221; is therefore a powerful argument for the spiritual qualities of honor, truth, and courage which marked the Anglo-Saxon mind before Christianity and the spiritual qualities of mercy, justice, and love after Christianity had spread. Cross has faith &amp; is like a thane. The Dream of the Rood also provides a valuable window into early Christian Anglo-Saxon England/Britain. Like most Old English poetry, it is written in alliterative verse. Preserved in the 10th century Vercelli Book discovered, in 1822, northern Italy the poem may be as old as the 8th century Ruthwell Cross, a large stone carving dating to the early eighth century. Eighteen verses of The Dream of the Rood were carved into the cross in runic lettering and it is considered one of the oldest works of Old English literature. The Dream of the Rood and the gospel tales of the crucifixion are separated not only by time, but by culture, language and depiction of the nature of Christ. The most obvious difference is that it is told from the POV of the cross whilst the biblical gospels are described by the apostles. In spite of this, there are clear parallels between the 2 accounts of crucifixion &#8211; both detail Christ&#8217;s death as a triumph of good over evil and redemption of mankind as a positive. Thus, these accounts follow the same event, but employ widely different methods of narration to explore greater themes.</p>

c8
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/2019/04/16/the-dream-of-the-rood/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
							</item>
	</channel>
</rss>

0

