<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>modern poet &#8211; NotesOfLit</title>
	<atom:link href="https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/category/modern-poet/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit</link>
	<description>A Site FIlled With Literary Notes</description>
	<lastBuildDate>
	Wed, 17 Apr 2019 12:42:28 +0000	</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.1.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/cropped-cropped-Logo-32x32-32x32.png</url>
	<title>modern poet &#8211; NotesOfLit</title>
	<link>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>A River By Attipate Krishnaswami</title>
		<link>https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/2019/04/17/a-river-by-attipate-krishnaswami/</link>
				<pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2019 12:30:04 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ayan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[modern poet]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[A River]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Attipate Krishnaswami Ramanujan]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://mominulislam23.github.io/notesoflit/?p=131</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[A River is written by Attipate Krishnaswami Ramanujan who is known as one of the greatest modern poet of India. The tone of the poem is based on sarcasm and irony. The structure of the poem has been in paragraphs and single lines. There are four longer verse paragraphs and &#8230;]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p class="has-drop-cap">A River is written by Attipate Krishnaswami Ramanujan who is known as one of the greatest modern poet of India. The tone of the poem is based on sarcasm and irony. The structure of the poem has been in paragraphs and single lines. There are four longer verse paragraphs and a shorter one in the beginning. There are only two single isolated lines. This kind of structural arrangement contributes to the effect of irony. It also helps to grasp the main points clearly.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<p>“A River” is a realistic description of the river Vaikai which flows through the city of Madurai. The poem implicitly comments wryly on the lack of realism with which other poets have treated the same topic. The poet has compared and contrasted the attitudes of the old poets and those of the new poets to human suffering. He has come to the conclusion that both the groups of the poets are not sympathetic, rather indifferent to human sorrow and suffering. This kind of attitude makes their poetry weak and unappealing, dry and cheerless. In the first stanza, Madurai is described as a “city of temples and poets,” making it sound like a place of great spiritual significance and associating it also with creativity and beauty. Its poets, indeed, have often sung of “cities and temples”, thereby celebrating places of great importance. Yet no sooner does the speaker make Madurai sound like a mythic, magnificent location than he immediately complicates this impression. He reports that each summer the city’s river—a river that might itself symbolize power, vitality, and energy—“dries to a trickle” uncovering “sand ribs”. He details the underbelly of the river that stays hidden. Visible now, are the bits of “straw and women’s hair” that chokes the rusty gates of the dam and the bridges that are plastered over with ‘patches of repair’. This stanza closes with a complain that all the poets ‘‘only sang of the floods’’. In stanza two, the poet speaks of the river in flood in the rains. He was there once and saw what happened. The river in spate destroys everything in its wake from live-stock to houses to human life. This happens once a year and has been continuing for years in the same pattern. He notes the casual approach of the of the towns people. Anxiously they talk of the rising level of water and enumerate mechanically the ‘precise’ number of steps as the water brims over the bathing places. The flood water “carried off three village houses,/ one pregnant woman/ and a couple of cows/ named Gopi and Brinda.” Humor is presented in the names of the cows and this too, is an attack on the orthodoxy of Hinduism. While cows are given names, no one knows who the pregnant woman is nor are they concerned. The third stanza opens with a complain that new poets have no wit but to blindly copy their predecessors and “no one spoke/ in verse/ of the pregnant woman”. The poet imagines that she may have drowned with not one life in her but two—“twins in her” which kicked “at blank walls even before birth”. He is sarcastic about both the new poets and old poets who seize only the floods to write about and that too merely once a year but did not refer to all these miseries of the woman in their poetic creations. The final stanza the poet mentions that “the river has water enough/ to be poetic” but only “once a year”. Maybe the river is beautiful and charming but it takes a heavy toll on human lives. It only takes “half-hour” to destroy “three village houses”, and take away the lives of humans and animals. This is an unusual poem with many layers of meaning and is a commentary on the indifference of the old and modern poets to the ravages caused by the river in flood and the pain and suffering caused to humans.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
										</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
